{"BOOK/?lang=eng":{"booklist":[{"title":"People of the Promised Land I2018","lessons":[{"id":"2018_1","name":"Lesson1 Joshua1:1-5:12 (09/10)"},{"id":"2018_2","name":"Lesson2 Joshua5:13-9:27 (09/17)"},{"id":"2018_3","name":"Lesson3 Joshua10-12 (09/24)"},{"id":"2018_4","name":"Lesson4 Joshua13-21 (10/1)"},{"id":"2018_5","name":"Lesson5 Joshua22-24 (10/08)"},{"id":"2018_6","name":"Lesson6 Ruth (10/15)"},{"id":"2018_7","name":"Lesson7 1Samuel1-3 (10/22)"},{"id":"2018_8","name":"Lesson8 1Samuel4-8 (10/29)"},{"id":"2018_9","name":"Lesson9 1Samuel9-15 (11/05)"},{"id":"2018_10","name":"Lesson10 1Samuel16-17 (11/12)"},{"id":"2018_11","name":"Lesson11 Psalms (11/19)"},{"id":"2018_12","name":"Lesson12 1Samuel18-20 (11/26)"},{"id":"2018_13","name":"Lesson13 1Samuel21-24 (12/03)"},{"id":"2018_14","name":"Lesson14 1Samuel25-27 (12/10)"},{"id":"2018_15","name":"Lesson15 1Samuel28-31 (01/07)"},{"id":"2018_16","name":"Lesson16 2Samuel1-4 (01/14)"},{"id":"2018_17","name":"Lesson17 2Samuel5-6;1Chronicles3:1-9;11-16 (01/21)"},{"id":"2018_18","name":"Lesson18 2Samuel7;1Chronicles17 (01/28)"},{"id":"2018_19","name":"Lesson19 2Samuel8-10 (02/04)"},{"id":"2018_20","name":"Lesson20 2Samuel11-12 (02/11)"},{"id":"2018_21","name":"Lesson21 2Samuel13-18 (02/18)"},{"id":"2018_22","name":"Lesson22 2Samuel19-24 (02/25)"},{"id":"2018_23","name":"Lesson23 1Kings1-2;1Chronicles22,28-29 (03/04)"},{"id":"2018_24","name":"Lesson24 1Kings3-4 (03/11)"},{"id":"2018_25","name":"Lesson25 Proverbs (03/18)"},{"id":"2018_26","name":"Lesson26 1Kings5-6 (03/25)"},{"id":"2018_27","name":"Lesson27 1Kings7-8;2Chronicles4:1-7:10 (04/1)"},{"id":"2018_28","name":"Lesson28 1Kings9-10 (04/15)"},{"id":"2018_29","name":"Lesson29 1Kings11 (04/22)"},{"id":"2018_30","name":"Lesson30 Joshua-1Kings11 (04/29)"}]},{"title":"Romans 2017-2018","lessons":[{"id":"2017_1","name":"Lesson1 Romans1:1-17 (09/18)","notesUri":"http://cbsf.azurewebsites.net/files/en-US/Romans_2017_01-manual.html"},{"id":"2017_2","name":"Lesson2 Romans1:18-32 (09/25)"},{"id":"2017_3","name":"Lesson3 Romans2 (10/02)"},{"id":"2017_4","name":"Lesson4 Romans3:1-20 (10/09)"},{"id":"2017_5","name":"Lesson5 Romans3:21-26 (10/16)"},{"id":"2017_6","name":"Lesson6 Romans3:27-31 (10/23)"},{"id":"2017_7","name":"Lesson7 Romans4 (10/30)"},{"id":"2017_8","name":"Lesson8 Romans5:1-11 (11/06)"},{"id":"2017_9","name":"Lesson9 Romans5:12-21 (11/13)"},{"id":"2017_10","name":"Lesson10 Romans6:1-11 (11/20)"},{"id":"2017_11","name":"Lesson11 Romans6:12-23 (11/27)"},{"id":"2017_12","name":"Lesson12 Romans7 (12/04)"},{"id":"2017_13","name":"Lesson13 Romans8:1-17 (12/11)"},{"id":"2017_14","name":"Lesson14 Romans8:18-27 (01/08)"},{"id":"2017_15","name":"Lesson15 Romans8:28-39 (01/15)"},{"id":"2017_16","name":"Lesson16 Romans9:1-29 (01/22)"},{"id":"2017_17","name":"Lesson17 Romans9:30-10:13 (01/29)"},{"id":"2017_18","name":"Lesson18 Romans10:14-21 (02/05)"},{"id":"2017_19","name":"Lesson19 Romans11:1-32 (02/12)"},{"id":"2017_20","name":"Lesson20 Romans11:33-36 (02/19)"},{"id":"2017_21","name":"Lesson21 Romans12:1-2 (02/26)"},{"id":"2017_22","name":"Lesson22 Romans12:3-8 (03/05)"},{"id":"2017_23","name":"Lesson23 Romans12:9-21 (03/12)"},{"id":"2017_24","name":"Lesson24 Romans13:1-7 (03/19)"},{"id":"2017_25","name":"Lesson25 Romans13:8-14 (03/26)"},{"id":"2017_26","name":"Lesson26 Romans14 (04/02)","homeTraining":true},{"id":"2017_27","name":"Lesson27 Romans15:1-13 (04/16)","homeTraining":true},{"id":"2017_28","name":"Lesson28 Romans15:14-33 (04/23)","homeTraining":true},{"id":"2017_29","name":"Lesson29 Romans16 (04/30)","homeDiscussion":true,"homeTraining":true},{"id":"2017_30","name":"Lesson30 Reflection (05/07)"}]}]},"LESSON/2018_1?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_1","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"There is no one holy like the Lord; there is no one besides you; there is no Rock like our God.\" – 1 Samuel 2:2","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_1_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_2","questionText":"2. What impacted you the most from the notes or lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Joshua 1:1-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"1:1-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_1_3","questionText":"3. What personal commission and promises did God give to Joshua? Which promise means the most to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_4a","questionText":"4. a. What are some significant attributes of God's commands to Joshua?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_4b","questionText":"4. b. What action did Joshua take after receiving them, and how might you apply these actions to your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_5","questionText":"5. How did Joshua handle the two and a half tribes (Reuben, Gad, Manasseh) who had settled on the eastern side of the Jordan? How would their response have encouraged him?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Joshua 2:1-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"2:1-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_1_6a","questionText":"6. a. How did Joshua get information about Jericho?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_6b","questionText":"6. b. How might Rahab have come to strong faith in God? What are the ways Rahab expressed her faith? (See also Hebrews 11:31 and James 2:18, 22, 25.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"11:31"},{"book":"James","verse":"2:18"},{"book":"James","verse":"2:22"},{"book":"James","verse":"2:25"}]},{"id":"2018_1_7","questionText":"7. What have you learned or experienced of God that gives you boldness to trust Him in a new or risky situation you face now?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_8","questionText":"8. How did God show favor to Rahab for trusting Him? (See Joshua 6:17-25 and Matthew 1:5-6.) How has He shown you favor as you have trusted in Him?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"6:17-25"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"1:5-6"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Joshua 3:1-4:24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"3:1-4:24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_1_9a","questionText":"9. a. What details stand out about the preparation for crossing the Jordan?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_9b","questionText":"9. b. What had Joshua told the people God would do? How did the crossing itself prove him right?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_10","questionText":"10. What was the ark? Why would it be significant that the priests carried it ahead of the people? (See Exodus 25:10-22; Hebrews 9:3-5.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"25:10-22"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"9:3-5"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Joshua 5:1-12.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"5:1-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_1_11","questionText":"11. What did God command Joshua to do, and why? (See Genesis 17:10-14; Exodus 12:48; Deuteronomy 30:6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:10-14"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"12:48"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"30:6"}]},{"id":"2018_1_12a","questionText":"12. a. What did the people celebrate after they healed? Why would this be meaningful? (See Numbers 9:1-5.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Numbers","verse":"9:1-5"}]},{"id":"2018_1_12b","questionText":"12. b. What else signified the end of their desert experience, and what hope would this give?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_1_13","questionText":"13. Where has God made a new way for you and given hope for new provision and fruitfulness? How will you thank Him for this?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Joshua 1:1-5:12.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"1:1-5:12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_1_14","questionText":"14. How did this week's study impact your thinking about God? How will that affect the actions you take in regard to a specific call of service, relationship, commitment or leadership position?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_2?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_2","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Have I not commanded you? Be strong and courageous. Do not be afraid; do not be discouraged, for the Lord your God will be with you wherever you go.\" – Joshua 1:9","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_2_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Joshua 5:13-6:27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"5:13-6:27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_2_3","questionText":"3. Who did Joshua meet near Jericho? Why might he have replied to Joshua's questions as he did?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_4a","questionText":"4. a. How would the Lord's words have encouraged Joshua, considering the walls of Jericho were tightly shut? What do they tell us about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_4b","questionText":"4. b. What was unique or interesting about the battle strategy? What effect might it have had on the Israelites and the residents of Jericho?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_5a","questionText":"5. a. What did God command the Israelites to do to Jericho, and why? Whom were they to spare, and why? (For help, see Genesis 15:16; Deuteronomy 12:29-32; Deuteronomy 20:16-18; Leviticus 18:24-28.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:16"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"12:29-32"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"20:16-18"},{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"18:24-28"}]},{"id":"2018_2_5b","questionText":"5. b. Describe any struggle you may have to reconcile God's wrath against sin and His love for people.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Joshua 7.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"7:1-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_2_6","questionText":"6. What was Joshua's response to the battle of Ai? What does his prayer reveal about his knowledge of and relationship with God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_7","questionText":"7. What did God reveal to Joshua? How did Achan respond when caught, and what resulted?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_8","questionText":"8. What consequences have you experienced because of wrongdoing (yours or others')?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Joshua 8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"8:1-35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_2_9a","questionText":"9. a. What do you learn about God from His words to Joshua before the battle?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_9b","questionText":"9. b. How did God's battle plan differ from the spies' plan in 7:3?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_10","questionText":"10. Why did Joshua read God's words to the entire assembly after the battle at Ai? (See Deuteronomy 11:26-30 and 27:2-8 for Moses' instructions.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"11:26-30"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"27:2-8"}]},{"id":"2018_2_11","questionText":"11. How can you share a love for and commitment to God's Word with your family and those around you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Joshua 9.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"9:1-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_2_12","questionText":"12. How did the surrounding nations respond to the Israelites' victories? What did this prompt the Gibeonites to do?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_2_13","questionText":"13. What should Joshua have done in response to the Gibeonites' request? Why did Joshua keep his promise to the Gibeonites? (See Exodus 34:12, 15; Numbers 30:2; Deuteronomy 7:2.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"34:12"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"34:15"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"30:2"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"7:2"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Joshua 5:13-9:27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"5:13-9:27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_2_14","questionText":"14. Through this week's lesson, how is God moving you to engage with the world, share a truth or show His love and kindness?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_3?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_3","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"The commander of the Lord's army replied, 'Take off your sandals, for the place where you are standing is holy.' And Joshua did so.\" – Joshua 5:15","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_3_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_3_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Joshua 10:1-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"10:1-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_3_3","questionText":"3. How did Joshua respond to the new challenge he faced? How did God encourage him?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_3_4","questionText":"4. What did God do supernaturally for Joshua and the Israelite army? What do these verses reveal about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_3_5","questionText":"5. What principles about integrity and prayer can you draw from these verses?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Joshua 10:16-43.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"10:16-43"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_3_6","questionText":"6. What was the reaction of the surrounding Canaanites after Joshua's armies returned from routing the armies of the five cities? What was the reason for it?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_3_7","questionText":"7. What did Joshua tell his men to do when they brought the five kings to him? What does this total victory point toward? (For help, see Psalm 110:1; Romans 16:20; 1 Corinthians 15:24-27 and any other Bible passages.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"110:1"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"16:20"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"15:24-27"}]},{"id":"2018_3_8","questionText":"8. How does the reality that God fights for His people encourage you as you fight against discouragement, temptation, worry, etc.?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Joshua 11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"11:1-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_3_9","questionText":"9. What command and promise did the Lord give Joshua as a large number of kings joined forces to fight Israel? What does it tell you about Joshua, his enemies and God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_3_10","questionText":"10. What was the significance of the destruction of the Anakites? (See Numbers 13:21-14:9; Deuteronomy 9:1-5 for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Numbers","verse":"13:21-14:9"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"9:1-5"}]},{"id":"2018_3_11","questionText":"11. What questions or doubts have you struggled with as you read these chapters describing violence and destruction?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Joshua 12.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"12:1-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_3_12","questionText":"12. Why would God include this list of defeated kings in the Bible? What does this chapter reveal about God's word, character and promises? (See Genesis 15:18-19; Exodus 23:31-33)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:18-19"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"23:31-33"}]},{"id":"2018_3_13","questionText":"13. What inspires you about Joshua?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_3_14","questionText":"14. What habits or practices in your life will you ask God to help you conquer?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Joshua 10-12.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"10:1-12:24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_3_15","questionText":"15. Choose one or more verses from this week's lesson, and quietly think deeply (meditate) on what is written. Are you taking these verses to heart and living them? Share with your group what God has revealed to you.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_4?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_4","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"All these kings and their lands Joshua conquered in one campaign, because the Lord, the God of Israel, fought for Israel.\" – Joshua 10:42","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_4_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_4_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Skim Joshua 13-14.\nJoshua 13-19 explain the division of the land among the tribes. Recurring themes include God faithfulness, His plans for each generation and the boundaries He sets.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"13:1-14:15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_4_3","questionText":"3. What does the allotment of land reveal about Moses, the Israelites and God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_4_4","questionText":"4. How does Caleb's story and request inspire you? (Read 14:6-14. Caleb's story is also recorded in Numbers 13:26-14:10, 20-24, 30, 36-38.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Numbers","verse":"13:26-14:10"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"14:20-24"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"14:30"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"14:36-38"}]},{"id":"2018_4_5","questionText":"5. How has God demonstrated His faithfulness as you have persevered through difficult seasons?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Skim Joshua 15-19.\nIn the details about land boundaries, look for how God keeps His promises to all without overlooking individuals or the need to prepare the next generation.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"15:1-19:51"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_4_6","questionText":"6. Why would God include these long, detailed lists of land boundaries and allotments in the Bible?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_4_7","questionText":"7. What do you learn about God's heart for women from Caleb's daughter and Zelophehad's daughters? (See Joshua 15:13-19; Joshua 17:3-6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"15:13-19"},{"book":"Joshua","verse":"17:3-6"}]},{"id":"2018_4_8","questionText":"8. How does Caleb's attitude and approach towards taking the land differ from the Manassites'? How does this encourage or challenge you? (See Joshua 14:6-15; Joshua 15:13-19; Joshua 17:7-18 for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"14:6-15"},{"book":"Joshua","verse":"15:13-19"},{"book":"Joshua","verse":"17:7-18"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Joshua 20 with Numbers 35:6-34.\nJoshua 20-21 describe the inheritance of the tribe of Levi, which served as priests for Israel. Joshua 20 especially highlights God's concern for justice and human life.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"20:1-9"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"35:6-34"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_4_9","questionText":"9. Describe the purpose and intent of the cities of refuge.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_4_10","questionText":"10. What do the cities of refuge reveal about God and His people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_4_11","questionText":"11. What do you learn about God in His provision of the cities of refuge that challenges, convicts or comforts you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Skim Joshua 21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"21:1-45"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_4_12","questionText":"12. What was the role of the Levites? Why did they receive cities instead of an inheritance of land? (See Numbers 18 for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Numbers","verse":"18:1-32"}]},{"id":"2018_4_13","questionText":"13. Why would it be beneficial to have the Levites spread out among all the tribes?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_4_14","questionText":"14. How does the New Testament describe the inheritance of believers? What \"deposit\" does God give believers as a guarantee? (See 1 Peter 1:3-5; Ephesians 1:13-14; 1 Corinthians 15:50-56 and any other Bible passages.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"1:3-5"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:13-14"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"15:50-56"}]},{"id":"2018_4_15","questionText":"15. What does Joshua 21:43-45 reveal about God? How do these truths reassure you in your present situation?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"21:43-45"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Joshua 13-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"13:1-21:45"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_4_16","questionText":"16. What did you learn about God, and what did you learn about yourself this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_5?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_5","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Not one of all the Lord's good promises to Israel failed; every one was fulfilled.\" – Joshua 21:45","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_5_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Joshua 22.\nJoshua 22 gives the account of the tribes of Reuben, Gad and half-tribe of Manasseh returning to their land east of\nthe Jordan River. The separation caused by the river caused some difficulties and fears for the 12 tribes.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"22:1-34"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_5_3","questionText":"3. How did Joshua commend and challenge the eastern tribes? (See Joshua 22:1-8.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"22:1-8"}]},{"id":"2018_5_4","questionText":"4. What did the western tribes fear after the eastern tribes built the altar? How did the eastern tribes defend their motives in building the altar? (For help, see Deuteronomy 12:10-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"12:10-14"}]},{"id":"2018_5_5","questionText":"5. What does this encounter teach you about dealing with confrontation in a God-honoring manner?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Joshua 23.\nJoshua 23 warns the Israelite leaders to remain devoted and obedient to the Lord.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"23:1-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_5_6","questionText":"6. What did Joshua want the Israelites to recognize and remember about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_7","questionText":"7. What truths about God can we learn from all He did for Israel?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_8","questionText":"8. How did Joshua instruct Israel? What was the danger for Israel should they choose to disobey?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_9","questionText":"9. Why would Joshua address the leaders separately? What does this teach you about the need for and value of godly leadership?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Joshua 24:1-13.\nJoshua 24 records Joshua's final reminders and warnings to the nation of Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"24:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_5_10","questionText":"10. What stands out to you in reading Israel's history, and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_11","questionText":"11. What does the retelling of Israel's history reveal about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_12","questionText":"12. Why is it important to read, tell and hear stories of God's past faithfulness? How do you or could you put that into practice?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Joshua 24:14-33.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"24:14-33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_5_13","questionText":"13. What choice did Joshua present to the nation? How do we make choices everyday about whom we will serve?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_14","questionText":"14. Why do you think Joshua did not readily accept their pledge to serve the Lord in verse 18? What lessons do you learn from Joshua's example?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_5_15","questionText":"15. What did Joshua mean by God's jealousy in 24:19? What examples can you think of where jealousy is an appropriate response? (See 2 Corinthians 11:2-4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"11:2-4"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Joshua 22-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"22:1-24:33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_5_16","questionText":"16. What would you like to see God do in your heart or in your life this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_6?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_6","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"But you are to hold fast to the Lord your God, as you have until now.\" – Joshua 23:8","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_6_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_6_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Ruth 1.\nRuth 1 explains why Elimelek moved his family to Moab and the events prior to Naomi's return to Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"1:1-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_6_3","questionText":"3. Describe Israel's relationship with Moab. What happened to Elimelek's family in Moab? (See Numbers 25:1-3; Deuteronomy 23:3-6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Numbers","verse":"25:1-3"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"23:3-6"}]},{"id":"2018_6_4","questionText":"4. What did Ruth potentially give up by going with Naomi? What did Ruth think she might gain by going with Naomi?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_6_5","questionText":"5. In what way has suffering and misfortune affected your attitude, family or decisions? How has your view of God been impacted by these situations?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Ruth 2.\nRuth gleaned in Boaz's field because God's law allowed the poor to glean the leftovers so they could eat.","readVerse":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"2:1-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_6_6","questionText":"6. Who was Boaz, and what character traits did he display? Why did he help Ruth, the Moabite? (See Matthew 1:5.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"1:5"}]},{"id":"2018_6_7","questionText":"7. What does Scripture tell us about Boaz's potential responsibility as a near relative (guardian-redeemer) of Elimelek? (See Leviticus 25:23-25; Deuteronomy 25:5-6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"25:23-25"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"25:5-6"}]},{"id":"2018_6_8","questionText":"8. How does this passage impact your heart toward the marginalized (poor, refugee, homeless, etc.)?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Ruth 3.\nRuth 3 relates Naomi's plan for Ruth and Boaz.","readVerse":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"3:1-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_6_9","questionText":"9. Why did Naomi resort to this plan? What were the potential pros and cons of the plan?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_6_10","questionText":"10. The Hebrew word translated \"garment\" in Ruth 3:9 is the same Hebrew word translated as \"wings\" in Ruth 2:12. What was Ruth saying to Boaz in her actions? Why would she say it in that way?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"3:9"},{"book":"Ruth","verse":"2:12"}]},{"id":"2018_6_11","questionText":"11. Give similarities and differences in how Boaz treated Ruth and how Jesus Christ treats those who come to Him. (You may use any additional Scripture references.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Ruth 4.\nRuth 4 gives perspective into ways God works through suffering for good.","readVerse":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"4:1-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_6_12","questionText":"12. What does \"redeem\" mean? Describe all the ways you see God's redemptive work in this chapter.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_6_13","questionText":"13. What do you know about David? Why would Scripture twice emphasize Obed's relationship to David? (See 2 Samuel 7:5-29, Matthew 1:1 or any other scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:5-29"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"1:1"}]},{"id":"2018_6_14","questionText":"14. How does this story give you hope as you wait on the Lord in your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Ruth 1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"1:1-4:22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_6_15","questionText":"15. What have you learned about God and Jesus your Redeemer in this week's study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_6_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Ruth 1-4","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"1:1-4:22"}]},{"id":"2018_6_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Ruth 1-4","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ruth","verse":"1:1-4:22"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_7?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_7","name":"","memoryVerse":"“The women said to Naomi: ‘Praise be to the LORD, who this day has not left you without a guardian-redeemer. May he become famous throughout Israel!’ ” – Ruth 4:14","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_7_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God’s activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 1.\nChapter 1 focuses on God’s gracious response to an Israelite woman enduring great disappointment.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"1:1-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_7_3","questionText":"3. What was Hannah’s situation at home, and how did she handle it?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_4","questionText":"4. What lessons can you learn from Eli’s interaction with Hannah? How might you apply those lessons in your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_5","questionText":"5. How does Hannah’s response reveal her faith and love for God? What challenges you personally from Hannah’s example?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 2:1-11.\nHannah offered Samuel to the Lord and responded with rejoicing and prayer.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"2:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_7_6","questionText":"6. What do you learn about God’s character and work from Hannah’s prayer? How does this help you in your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_7","questionText":"7. Who else in Scripture was willing to sacrifice their son for God’s glory? What are you willing to sacrifice in order to bring glory to God? (Use any scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_8","questionText":"8. What does Hannah’s prayer reveal about God’s future plans?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 2:12-36.\nChapters 2-3 reveal a contrast between Eli’s family and Samuel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"2:12-36"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_7_9","questionText":"9. Describe the sins of Eli’s sons and Eli’s response to their sin. (See also Leviticus 7:28-36.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"7:28-36"}]},{"id":"2018_7_10","questionText":"10. What did God promise would happen to Eli’s family because of their unwillingness to repent?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_11","questionText":"11. What behaviors (of yours or of others close to you) are you tempted to ignore or enable? How is God inviting you to respond?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 3.\nGod spoke and revealed His plans through Samuel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"3:1-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_7_12","questionText":"12. What stands out to you about God’s interactions with Samuel and Samuel’s interactions with Eli?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_13","questionText":"13. What does this chapter reveal about the privilege and the responsibility of being the Lord’s servant?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_7_14","questionText":"14. What has God revealed to you in His Word? How can you make known God’s Word to others?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 1-3.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"1:1-3:21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_7_15","questionText":"15. What attribute of God resonated most from your study of this week’s passage? How do you see that attribute displayed in the world today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_8?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_8","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"The Lord came and stood there, calling as at the other times, 'Samuel, Samuel!' Then Samuel said, 'Speak, for your servant is listening.' \" – 1 Samuel 3:10","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_8_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 4-5.\nGod revealed His power over the Philistine gods.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"4:1-5:12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_8_3","questionText":"3. What was the ark of the covenant? What did the Israelites hope to accomplish by taking it into battle? (See Exodus 25:10-22; Numbers 7:89; 1 Samuel 4:22; Hebrews 9:1-4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"25:10-22"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"7:89"},{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"4:22"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"9:1-4"}]},{"id":"2018_8_4","questionText":"4. Trace the effects of the ark's presence in these chapters. What lessons do you learn about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_5","questionText":"5. How are Christians guilty of trying to use God or His Word to get what they want today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 6.\nGod revealed His power and holiness to the Philistines and Israelites as the ark was returned to Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"6:1-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_8_6","questionText":"6. How did the Philistines combine their knowledge and fear of God with superstition? Give examples of how believers and unbelievers do this today.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_7","questionText":"7. What happened once the ark was returned to Beth Shemesh (Israel)? How do believers trample on God's holiness today? (See Numbers 4:5-6, 20.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Numbers","verse":"4:5-6"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"4:20"}]},{"id":"2018_8_8","questionText":"8. What do you learn about God's character in this passage? How does that encourage you in your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 7.\nSamuel led and interceded for Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"7:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_8_9","questionText":"9. How did Samuel demonstrate godly leadership? Which examples will you implement with your family, children or others you lead?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_10","questionText":"10. How did the Israelites demonstrate faith and true repentance? What were the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_11","questionText":"11. Compare and contrast the battles in chapters 4 and 7. What lessons can you learn from these two battles?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 8.\nSamuel warned the Israelites of the consequences for insisting on an earthly king.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"8:1-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_8_12","questionText":"12. Why did the Israelites ask for a king? What did Samuel say would be the cost of having a king?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_13","questionText":"13. What do you learn about God or people in this passage?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_8_14","questionText":"14. How do believers try to be like the world today? At what cost?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 4-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"4:1-8:22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_8_15","questionText":"15. How did this week's study impact your thinking about repentance, grace, faith or obedience?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_9?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_9","name":"","memoryVerse":"“Then Samuel took a stone and set it up between Mizpah and Shen. He named it Ebenezer, saying, ‘Thus far the LORD has helped us.’ ” – 1 Samuel 7:12","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_9_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God’s activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 9-10.\nGod directed Samuel to anoint and instruct Saul as Israel’s first king.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"9:1-10:27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_9_3","questionText":"3. How did God reveal Saul was His choice for Israel’s first king?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_4","questionText":"4. What signs and instructions did Samuel give Saul?  What does this reveal about the king’s relationship to God and His prophets?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_5","questionText":"5. What do you learn about God’s call to a specific work? What is the work God has for you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 11.\nGod granted Saul and the Israelites victory over the Ammonites.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"11:1-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_9_6","questionText":"6. What difficult situation did the people face? What seemingly impossible situation are you facing or have faced in the past?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_7","questionText":"7. What changes were evident in Saul when the Holy Spirit came upon him? (1 Samuel 10:22-26)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"10:22-26"}]},{"id":"2018_9_8","questionText":"8. How has the Holy Spirit’s indwelling changed and empowered you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 12-13.\nSamuel instructed Israel to remember the Lord, but Saul ignored his instructions.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"12:1-13:23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_9_9","questionText":"9. In Samuel’s farewell speech, what did he say about himself, God and the people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_10","questionText":"10. How did the people respond? How did Samuel instruct and encourage them?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_11","questionText":"11. Why did Saul disobey Samuel’s instructions? What were the consequences for Saul’s disobedience? (1 Samuel 10:8)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"10:8"}]},{"id":"2018_9_12","questionText":"12. What pressures to disobey do you face? How have you been impacted by your own or other’s disobedience to God?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 14-15.\nSaul demonstrated unwise and ungodly leadership before God rejected him as king.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"14:1-15:35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_9_13","questionText":"13. How does Jonathan’s courage and reliance on God in His battle against the Philistines inspire you? (1 Samuel 14:1-23)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"14:1-23"}]},{"id":"2018_9_14","questionText":"14. What do the events in this battle reveal about Saul’s character and leadership?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_15","questionText":"15. How did Saul excuse his disobedience? What excuses do you or others offer for your disobedience?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_9_16","questionText":"16. What do you learn about God through Saul’s failures? How does this comfort or challenge you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 9-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"9:1-15:35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_9_17","questionText":"17. What was your biggest takeaway from your personal study of this week’s lesson?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_10?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_10","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"For the sake of his great name the Lord will not reject his people, because the Lord was pleased to make you his own.\" – 1 Samuel 12:22","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_10_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 16:1-13 with 15:34-35.\nGod directed Samuel to anoint David as the next king of Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"16:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_10_3","questionText":"3. How did God address Samuel's sorrow and misgivings? What lesson(s) do you learn?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_4","questionText":"4. What insights did the Lord give Samuel as he considered Jesse's sons? How do those insights challenge, warn or impact you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_5","questionText":"5. What do you learn about the way God views people? How does this compare to what you value in yourself and others? (See also Psalm 44:21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"44:21"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 16:14-23.\nNewly anointed David began to serve King Saul.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"16:14-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_10_6","questionText":"6. What happened to Saul? What might have been some reasons it occurred? (For help, see Deuteronomy 28:15, 28; 1 Samuel 15:16-29; Lamentations 3:39.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"28:15"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"28:28"},{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"15:16-29"},{"book":"Lamentations","verse":"3:39"}]},{"id":"2018_10_7","questionText":"7. How did God move David from the shepherd's fields to serving in the palace? What characteristics are evident in David as he served Saul?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_8","questionText":"8. Where and how has God called you to use the gifts He has given you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 17:1-32.\nDavid arrived at the battleground and assessed the threat.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"17:1-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_10_9","questionText":"9. What threat did Saul and the Israelite army face? How did they respond?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_10","questionText":"10. How did Goliath taunt the Israelites? What was his idea to settle the battle?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_11","questionText":"11. How did David's perspective differ from his brothers' and the other soldiers'? What do their words and actions reveal about their belief in God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_12","questionText":"12. In your present circumstances, what do your words and actions reveal about your belief in God?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 17:33-58.\nThe Lord saved the Israelites through David's victory.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"17:33-58"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_10_13","questionText":"13. How did David's prior experiences of God's power give him courage to face this challenge? How does this help or encourage you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_14","questionText":"14. How did David's actions and words to Saul, the Israelites and Goliath express his absolute confidence in God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_15","questionText":"15. In what specific ways could you follow David's example in your own present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_10_16","questionText":"16. From this passage, what similarities are there between David and Jesus Christ? (Use any Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 16-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"16:1-17:58"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_10_17","questionText":"17. What would you like to see God do in your life this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_11?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_11","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"The Lord does not look at the things people look at. People look at the outward appearance, but the Lord looks at the heart.\" – 1 Samuel 16:7b","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_11_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_11_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Psalm 139.\nPsalms compile song lyrics and prayers from many authors. This lesson focuses on the Psalms David wrote.","readVerse":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"139:1-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_11_3","questionText":"3. What do you learn about God's universal and personal knowledge and power?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_11_4","questionText":"4. How does David's longing and request reveal his zeal for God and hatred of sin? How can a Christian balance hatred of sin and love for those opposed to God today? (Psalm 139:19-24)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"139:19-24"}]},{"id":"2018_11_5","questionText":"5. How is this Psalm relevant to your present circumstances? (Are you trying to run from Him, being honest with Him, feeling persecuted, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Psalms 7 and 10.\nPsalms 7 and 10 demonstrate praise and petition through suffering.","questions":[{"id":"2018_11_6","questionText":"6. Which attributes of God stand out to you? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_11_7","questionText":"7. What do these psalms reveal about those who perpetrate wickedness and those who are afflicted?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_11_8","questionText":"8. Who and what is David's constant hope? Who and what is your hope?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Psalm 19\nDavid praised God's revelation in creation and His Word.","readVerse":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"19:1-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_11_9","questionText":"9. God's glory has been defined as the sum total of His attributes. What attributes of God are revealed through creation? (Use any Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_11_10","questionText":"10. How does David describe God's Word? How is your attitude toward God's Word similar or different?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_11_11","questionText":"11. How does David describe the benefits of studying God's Word? What specific differences has studying God's Word made in you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Psalms 2 and 110.\nDavid pleaded for deliverance often and in confident, prophetic anticipation of Jesus Christ.","questions":[{"id":"2018_11_12","questionText":"12. What is the complaint against God in Psalm 2:1-3? How does this compare with people's complaints against God today?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"2:1-3"}]},{"id":"2018_11_13","questionText":"13. What is God's gracious answer to the world's rebellion? How can God justly spare all the wicked who take refuge in his Son? (See Psalm 2:4-13 and Isaiah 53:4-6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"2:4-13"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"53:4-6"}]},{"id":"2018_11_14","questionText":"14. What does Psalm 110 reveal about Jesus? (For help, see Acts 2:33-36; Mark 14:61-62; Hebrews 1:13; 4:14-16; 7:11-8:2 or any other scripture references.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"110:1-7"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"2:33-36"},{"book":"Mark","verse":"14:61-62"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"1:13"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"4:14-16"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"7:11-8:2"}]},{"id":"2018_11_15","questionText":"15. What conviction, confidence or hope do these psalms give you today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Psalms 2, 7, 10, 19, 110, 139.","questions":[{"id":"2018_11_16","questionText":"16. Choose one or more verses from this week's lesson, and quietly think deeply (meditate) on what is written. How is God calling you to take to heart and act on these verses? Share with your group what God has revealed to you.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_12?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_12","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"All the ends of the earth will remember and turn to the Lord, and all the families of the nations will bow down before him.\" – Psalm 22:27","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_12_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_12_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 18.\nDavid experienced strained relations with Saul and strong relationships with Saul's children.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"18:1-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_12_3","questionText":"3. What is most interesting to you concerning David's relationships with Saul, Jonathan and Michal. Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_12_4","questionText":"4. What lessons or warnings do you learn from Saul? In what area of your life could you apply these lessons?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_12_5","questionText":"5. How does David experience both the blessing and cost of following God? How have you seen both the blessing and cost of following Jesus in your own life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 19 with Psalm 59.\nSaul's children protected David from their father.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"19:1-24"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"59:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_12_6","questionText":"6. What risks did Jonathan and Michal take to protect David?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_12_7","questionText":"7. Where is God calling you to do what is right even at personal cost or risk to yourself?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_12_8","questionText":"8. How does Psalm 59 deepen your insight into David's faith and the danger he faced? How did David's faith strengthen him?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"59:1-17"}]},{"id":"2018_12_9","questionText":"9. How might describing and naming God in your prayers transform your present outlook?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 20.\nDavid and Jonathan prepared a plan to protect David from Saul.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"20:1-42"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_12_10","questionText":"10. What do you learn about Jonathan through his words and actions? What do you find most commendable? (1 Samuel 18-20)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"18:1-20:42"}]},{"id":"2018_12_11","questionText":"11. Why would Jonathan give loyalty to David instead of Saul? What does Jonathan seem to understand about David? (Use any Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_12_12","questionText":"12. What does David's and Jonathan's relationship teach you about true friendship?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Psalms 23 and 36.\nDavid praised God for His protection and love.","questions":[{"id":"2018_12_13","questionText":"13. How does David describe God's tender care in Psalm 23? Which aspect of God's care is most meaningful to you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"23:1-6"}]},{"id":"2018_12_14","questionText":"14. How does David's understanding of the sinfulness of the wicked compare to your view of sin? (Psalm 36)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"36:1-12"}]},{"id":"2018_12_15","questionText":"15. How does David's understanding of God help you today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 18-20 with Psalms 23, 36, and 59.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"18:1-20:42"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_12_16","questionText":"16. What have you learned in this week's study about God or about the suffering of every believer?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_13?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_13","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"In everything [David] did he had great success, because the Lord was with him.\" – 1 Samuel 18:14","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_13_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 21 and Psalm 34.\nDavid escaped from King Saul and acknowledged God's provision and protection.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"21:1-15"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"34:1-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_13_3","questionText":"3. What are some possible ways to interpret David's and Ahimelek's interaction? Who else was present? (See Luke 6:1-5.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Luke","verse":"6:1-5"}]},{"id":"2018_13_4","questionText":"4. What prompted David's fear in Gath? How did David escape?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_5a","questionText":"5. a. What does Psalm 34 reveal about David's thinking during his circumstances and escape?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"34:1-22"}]},{"id":"2018_13_5b","questionText":"5. b. How does Psalm 34 encourage or challenge you in your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"34:1-22"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 22 and Psalm 52.\n1 Samuel 22 contrasted Saul and David's role and response in the priests' death.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"22:1-23"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"52:1-9"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_13_6","questionText":"6. What do you learn about Saul from his words and actions? What warnings or lessons do you find?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_7","questionText":"7. What do you learn about David from his words and actions? What warnings or lessons do you find?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_8","questionText":"8. What does Psalm 52 reveal about David's understanding of good and evil? How does this compare with your views?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"52:1-9"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 23 and Psalm 54.\nGod guided David into victory and safety.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"23:1-29"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"54:1-7"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_13_9","questionText":"9. With whom did David consult each time before he took any action? How does that compare with your practice?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_10","questionText":"10. What do you learn about God in 1 Samuel 23?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"23:1-29"}]},{"id":"2018_13_11","questionText":"11. How did God encourage and protect David? How does this encourage you to trust God's leading and direction?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_12","questionText":"12. What truths about God did David recall in Psalm 54? Which truths about God are most comforting to you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"54:1-7"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 24 and Psalms 57 and 142.\nDavid spared Saul's life.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"24:1-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_13_13","questionText":"13. What assumptions did David's men make when they met Saul in the cave? How are we guilty of making similar assumptions today?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_14","questionText":"14. What reasons did David give for not killing Saul? How do David's words and actions demonstrate his deep desire to honor God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_15","questionText":"15. In what situation is God inviting you to do the right yet difficult thing and to trust Him with the outcome?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_16","questionText":"16. According to Psalm 57 and 142 what is David's ultimate prayer? How might this change the way you pray about your circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"57:1-11"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"142:1-7"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 21-24 and Psalms 34, 52, 54, 57 and 142.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"21:1-24:22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_13_17","questionText":"17. God described David as a man after his own heart. How did David reflect God's character in these chapters? Which qualities will you ask God to grow in you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_13_18","questionText":"18. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: 1 Samuel 21-24","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"21:1-24:22"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_14?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_14","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Surely God is my help; the Lord is the one who sustains me.\" – Psalm 54:4","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_14_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_14_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 25:1-13.\nDavid's anger escalated when Nabal rejected his request.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"25:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_14_3","questionText":"3. Describe Nabal's character. Which qualities of Nabal do you see in yourself?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_14_4","questionText":"4. What do you learn about David through Nabal's rejection? How does David's impulsive reaction nearly result in great suffering?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_14_5","questionText":"5. Who is at risk of being hurt when you do not get your way? How might God be warning you through this passage?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 25:14-44 with Psalm 37.\nGod used Abigail to appease David's anger.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"25:14-44"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"37:1-40"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_14_6","questionText":"6. Describe Abigail's character. (See 1 Samuel 25:3.) Which qualities would you like God to develop in you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"25:3"}]},{"id":"2018_14_7","questionText":"7. How did God extend mercy to David in spite of his anger? Share a time God extended mercy to you. 8. What stands out to you in Psalm 37? How do these verses apply to you and your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"37:1-40"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 26.\nDavid encountered and spared Saul.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"26:1-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_14_9","questionText":"9. How might David's earlier encounters with Saul and Nabal have affected his decisions and behavior in this encounter with Saul? (See 1 Samuel 24-25 for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"24:1-25:44"}]},{"id":"2018_14_10","questionText":"10. Compare and contrast David's and Abishai's assessment of the situation. Why did David spare Saul's life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_14_11","questionText":"11. What does David's speech to Saul reveal about God? Which truths will you ask God to help you remember?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 27.\nDavid and his men left Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"27:1-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_14_12","questionText":"12. What motivated David's reasons for moving to Gath? Were his reasons valid? Why or why not?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_14_13","questionText":"13. When has your faith been tested? How did you deal with it?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_14_14","questionText":"14. What assurances does God give to those who put their faith in Him? Which promises encourage you in your present situation? (See John 10:27-30; Romans 8:30-39; Philippians 1:6 or other Scriptures you may know for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"10:27-30"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:30-39"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"1:6"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 25-27 with Psalm 37.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"25:1-27:12"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"37:1-40"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_14_15","questionText":"15. What attribute of God resonated most from your study of this week's passage? How do you see that attribute displayed in the world today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_15?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_15","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"The Lord your God will certainly make a lasting dynasty for my lord, because you fight the Lord's battles, and no wrongdoing will be found in you as long as you live.\" – 1 Samuel 25:28b","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_15_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Samuel 28.\nSaul secretly consulted a medium for help.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"28:1-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_15_3","questionText":"3. What fears might David and Saul had about the battle? How did their fears influence their behavior?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_4","questionText":"4. What is wrong with consulting a medium? How do you respond when a friend or superior asks you to participate in an unethical situation? (See Leviticus 19:31 and 1 Chronicles 10:13-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"19:31"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"10:13-14"}]},{"id":"2018_15_5","questionText":"5. Where do you turn when it seems the Lord is silent or not telling you want you want to hear?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Samuel 29.\nDavid was released from fighting against Israel.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"29:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_15_6","questionText":"6. What conflict arose between Achish and his men?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_7","questionText":"7. How do you see God at work in David's situation?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_8","questionText":"8. How have you seen God's protection in your own life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 30 with Psalm 36.\nDavid and his men defeated the Amalekites and shared the plunder.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"30:1-31"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"36:1-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_15_9","questionText":"9. Describe the scene at Ziklag. How did David and his men respond?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_10","questionText":"10. What leadership qualities do you see in David? Which ones will you ask the Lord to develop in you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_11","questionText":"11. How does Psalm 36 encourage you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"36:1-12"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Samuel 31 with 1 Chronicles 10.\nSaul took his own life.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"31:1-13"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"10:1-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_15_12","questionText":"12. Describe the events surrounding Saul's death. Who took care of the bodies of Saul and his sons? (See 1 Samuel 11:1-11.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"11:1-11"}]},{"id":"2018_15_13","questionText":"13. How might God be calling you to go out of your way to do something honorable or compassionate?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_15_14","questionText":"14. What was the summation of Saul's life? What do you hope will be said of you in relation to the Lord at the end of your life? (See 1 Chronicles 10:13-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"10:13-14"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Samuel 28-31 with 1 Chronicles 10, and Psalm 36.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"28:1-31:13"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"10:1-14"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"36:1-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_15_15","questionText":"15. How did this week's study impact your thinking about the necessity to seek and trust God's guidance rather than looking to the world for wisdom?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_16?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_16","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"For with you is the fountain of life; in your light we see light.\" – Psalm 36:9","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_16_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 1.\nDavid grieved Saul's and Jonathan's deaths.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"1:1-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_16_3","questionText":"3. How did the man's report of Saul's death compare with the actual events? Why might he have changed the story? (See 1 Samuel 31:1-7.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"31:1-7"}]},{"id":"2018_16_4","questionText":"4. Why was David unwilling to celebrate Saul's death? What does that say about David's relationship with and beliefs about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_5","questionText":"5. What does David's response to the news reveal about him? Which qualities will you ask God to grow in you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 2:1-3:5.\nDavid's and Saul's men battled over who would be Israel's next king.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"2:1-3:5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_16_6","questionText":"6. What decision did David face? How did David decide what to do next? (See 1 Samuel 16:12-13 and 2 Samuel 2:1-3.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"16:12-13"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"2:1-3"}]},{"id":"2018_16_7","questionText":"7. Did Abner's actions make the situation better or worse between David's and Saul's men? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_8","questionText":"8. What reminders, warnings or examples do you see in this passage? How could you apply them to your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 3:6-29.\nAbner shifted his loyalty to David and was killed.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"3:6-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_16_9","questionText":"9. What prompted Abner's change in loyalty? How did Abner demonstrate his loyalty to David?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_10","questionText":"10. What do you learn from the differences in how David and Joab responded to Abner? How do you respond to those who have hurt or harmed you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_11","questionText":"11. How do you see God working to establish David as king, in the good and hard times?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 4:1-12.\nDavid ordered the execution of Ish-Bosheth's murderers.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"4:1-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_16_12","questionText":"12. What were Saul's men hoping to gain by killing Ish-Bosheth? What were the consequences?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_13","questionText":"13. How do you see people engaging in self-promotion today? Which are most tempting to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_16_14","questionText":"14. What do you learn about choices and consequences from this passage?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"1:1-4:12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_16_15","questionText":"15. Through this week's lesson, how is God challenging your view of the purpose of struggles or to remain patient instead of taking matters into your own hands?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_17?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_17","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"The precepts of the Lord are right, giving joy to the heart. The commands of the Lord are radiant, giving light to the eyes.\" – Psalm 19:8","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_17_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_17_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 5:1-16.\nThe Lord established David as Israel's king.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"5:1-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_17_3","questionText":"3. What reasons did Israel's tribes give for making David king? How did David's rise to power validate God's call and years of waiting? (1 Samuel 16:11-13)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"16:11-13"}]},{"id":"2018_17_4","questionText":"4. What characteristics does David exhibit in these verses? What opportunities is God giving you to develop these characteristics?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_17_5","questionText":"5. How did David understand the reason and purpose for his success? Where has God placed you so you will bless those around you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 5:17-25 and Psalm 68.\nGod delivered David from the Philistines twice.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"5:17-25"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"68:1-35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_17_6","questionText":"6. How did David respond to the Philistine threat? When have you recently prayed for wisdom and direction? What were the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_17_7","questionText":"7. From Psalm 68, for what attributes of God does David praise God?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"68:1-35"}]},{"id":"2018_17_8","questionText":"8. What encourages or challenges you most about David's worship and understanding of God?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 6:1-11; 1 Chronicles 13:1-14.\nDavid disobeyed God's instructions for moving the ark.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"6:1-11"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"13:1-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_17_9","questionText":"9. Why might David want the ark of the covenant in Jerusalem? Who confirmed his plans?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_17_10","questionText":"10. Why did God respond the way He did? What lessons do you learn? (Exodus 25:10-22; Numbers 4:5-6, 15)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"25:10-22"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"4:5-6"},{"book":"Numbers","verse":"4:15"}]},{"id":"2018_17_11","questionText":"11. How has this study challenged or enlarged your view of God? How will this impact the way you live?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 6:12-23; 1 Chronicles 15:1-16:43.\nDavid brought the ark to Jerusalem with great celebration.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"6:12-23"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"15:1-16:43"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_17_12","questionText":"12. What differences did you notice when the ark was moved the second time? What do you learn from that?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_17_13","questionText":"13. How did David celebrate his love and thankfulness to God? For what will you celebrate and thank God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_17_14","questionText":"14. How did Michal respond to David's expressive worship? What can you learn from David's response when others ridicule you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 5-6; 1 Chronicles 11:1-9; 12:1-16:43; Psalm 68.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"5:1-6:23"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"11:1-9"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"12:1-16:43"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"68:1-35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_17_15","questionText":"15. What was your biggest takeaway from your personal study of this week's lesson?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_18?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_18","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Look to the Lord and his strength; seek his face always.\" – 1 Chronicles 16:11","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_18_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 7:1-7; 1 Chronicles 17:1-6; 22:8; 28:3.\nGod rejected David's request to build God a house.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:1-7"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"17:1-6"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"22:8"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"28:3"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_18_3","questionText":"3. What did David want to do for the Lord? Why? Was God pleased with David's request? (2 Chronicles 6:8)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"6:8"}]},{"id":"2018_18_4","questionText":"4. What reasons did God give David for not proceeding? What do you learn about God from these reasons?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_5","questionText":"5. When have you had God say \"no\" to something you wanted? What lessons did you learn?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 7:8-17; 1 Chronicles 17:7-15; Psalm 89:35-37.\nGod promised to build David a dynasty.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:8-17"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"17:7-15"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"89:35-37"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_18_6","questionText":"6. What were the main promises of God's covenant with David? To what New Testament person does it ultimately refer? (For help, see Isaiah 9:6-7; Matthew 1:1-16 or any other Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"9:6-7"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"1:1-16"}]},{"id":"2018_18_7","questionText":"7. What warnings and encouragements stand out to you from these promises?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_8","questionText":"8. Looking back, how has God revealed His wisdom and love through His plans for your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 7:18-24; 1 Chronicles 17:16-22.\nDavid marveled at God's matchless greatness.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:18-24"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"17:16-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_18_9","questionText":"9. Describe David's response to God.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_10","questionText":"10. Which of David's thoughts and beliefs about God are most meaningful to you? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_11","questionText":"11. What did David recognize God doing for himself, his family and Israel? How have you seen and responded to unexpected blessings in your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 7:25-29; 1 Chronicles 17:23-27; Psalm 89:19-37.\nDavid prayed for God's continued blessing.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:25-29"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"17:23-27"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"89:19-37"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_18_12","questionText":"12. Define \"covenant\" using a dictionary. Was God's covenant with David conditional or unconditional? Explain.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_13","questionText":"13. What reasons did David give for his courage and confidence to pray? How does God encourage you to pray?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_18_14","questionText":"14. Though not written by David, Psalm 89 is often read along with God's covenant in 2 Samuel 7. From the Psalm, how are God's covenant and God's love linked together?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"89:1-52"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:1-29"}]},{"id":"2018_18_15","questionText":"15. From the psalm, how does God describe Himself? How would remembering these attributes help you in your current situation?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 7; 1 Chronicles 17; Psalm 89:19-37.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"7:1-29"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"17:1-27"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"89:19-37"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_18_16","questionText":"16. What did you learn about God, and what did you learn about yourself?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_19?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_19","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Your house and your kingdom will endure forever before me; your throne will be established forever.\" – 2 Samuel 7:16","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_19_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 8.\nKing David defeated Israel's enemies.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"8:1-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_19_3","questionText":"3. Note the nations David subdued. What did these victories mean for David and the nation of Israel?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_4","questionText":"4. What repeated sentence reveals the true reason for David's military success? What are some ways people today acknowledge God in their successes?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_5","questionText":"5. How did David use the articles and plunder he collected from the defeated nations? What would it look like to dedicate resources to God in your culture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_6","questionText":"6. Describe David's leadership and character. How would you like those over whom you hold power or influence describe you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 9.\nDavid found Mephibosheth and cared for him as a son.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"9:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_19_7","questionText":"7. Why did David want to find someone in Saul's family? What does this tell you about him? (See also 1 Samuel 20:14-15, 42.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"20:14-15"},{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"20:42"}]},{"id":"2018_19_8","questionText":"8. What promises did David make to members of Saul's household? When have you given or received something undeserved?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_9","questionText":"9. How do you treat the marginalized and forgotten in your society? To whom is God reminding you to show kindness?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 9; Ephesians 2:1-10.\nDavid reflected Jesus through the grace he extended to Mephibosheth.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"9:1-13"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_19_10","questionText":"10. Describe God's love, grace, mercy and salvation from Ephesians 2:1-10.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-10"}]},{"id":"2018_19_11","questionText":"11. How is David's treatment of Mephibosheth similar to God's grace and mercy in Christ Jesus? (Use any Bible passage, such as John 3:16-18; Romans 3:23-25; 8:15-30; Ephesians 1:3-8.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"3:16-18"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:23-25"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:15-30"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:3-8"}]},{"id":"2018_19_12","questionText":"12. When and how have you experienced God's mercy? How will you express your gratitude to God?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 10; Psalm 60.\nDavid defeated the Ammonites and Arameans.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"10:1-19"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"60:1-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_19_13","questionText":"13. What misunderstanding resulted in the Ammonites' conflict with Israel? How have you faced similar circumstances? What were the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_14","questionText":"14. Even though Joab made and executed a battle plan, what was the source of Joab's confidence? What do you learn that you can apply in your present situation?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_19_15","questionText":"15. Psalm 60 was written in response to the events of 2 Samuel 8 and 10. How does this psalm encourage or challenge you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"60:1-12"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"8:1-18"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"10:1-19"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 8-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"8:1-10:19"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_19_16","questionText":"16. What would you like to see God do in your life this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_20?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_20","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Be strong, and let us fight bravely for our people and the cities of our God. The Lord will do what is good in his sight.\" – 2 Samuel 10:12","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_20_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 11:1-17.\nDavid ordered a murder to cover his adultery.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"11:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_20_3","questionText":"3. Describe the steps leading to David's sins. What do you learn from this?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_4","questionText":"4. How have you or will you establish protections to prevent yourself from giving in to temptation?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_5","questionText":"5. What resources did God provide David to help him in times of weakness? (See Deuteronomy 17:18-20 and 1 Samuel 16:12-13.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"17:18-20"},{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"16:12-13"}]},{"id":"2018_20_6","questionText":"6. What additional resources does God provide His people today? Which are most helpful to you? (For help see Ecclesiastes 4:9-10, John 14:26, Romans 8:34, 1 Corinthians 10:13, Hebrews 4:14-16 or any other Scripture verse.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"4:9-10"},{"book":"John","verse":"14:26"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:34"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"10:13"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"4:14-16"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 11:18-27 with Psalm 32.\nDavid married Bathsheba after Uriah was killed.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"11:18-27"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"32:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_20_7","questionText":"7. Describe how David's sin and cover-up affected others.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_8","questionText":"8. Describe how David's sin and cover-up affected himself.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_9","questionText":"9. What lessons from David's experience can you learn and apply to your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 12:1-23 with Psalm 51.\nDavid repented after Nathan confronted him about his sin.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"12:1-23"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"51:1-19"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_20_10","questionText":"10. What do you learn about David through Nathan's encounter and the subsequent consequences? What is important to remember whether you are the one confronted or confronting another?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_11","questionText":"11. From both passages, what did David believe about God? How do these attributes of God challenge or comfort you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_12","questionText":"12. What lessons do you learn concerning repentance and forgiveness? Which lesson is most helpful in your present circumstances? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 12:24-31.\nDavid fathered Solomon and conquered the Ammonites.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"12:24-31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_20_13","questionText":"13. How did God restore David?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_14","questionText":"14. How did both Nathan and Joab prompt David? What qualities did Nathan and Joab demonstrate?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_20_15","questionText":"15. How have you experienced God's grace in your own life? How and to whom might you extend grace?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 11-12 with Psalms 32 and 51.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"11:1-12:31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_20_16","questionText":"16. What is the most important or challenging thing you learned this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_21?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_21","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Have mercy on me, O God, according to your unfailing love; according to your great compassion blot out my transgressions.\" – Psalm 51:1","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_21_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_21_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 13.\nDavid's son Amnon raped his half-sister Tamar, and his half-brother Absalom killed him.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"13:1-39"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_21_3a","questionText":"3. a. What alarming signs do you see in Amnon's behavior? What sins did he commit? (See Exodus 20:1-17 and Leviticus 18:9.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"20:1-17"},{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"18:9"}]},{"id":"2018_21_3b","questionText":"3. b. What do you learn about the devastation that follows unchecked sin? How can people establish safeguards to protect against sin from going this far?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_21_4","questionText":"4. What do you learn from the ways the men in this passage reacted to Tamar's rape? What did God's law require? (See Leviticus 18:9-11 and Deuteronomy 22:25-27.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"18:9-11"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"22:25-27"}]},{"id":"2018_21_5","questionText":"5. What scriptures emphasize God's comfort and compassion for the hurting and brokenhearted? How might these verses comfort you or others? (Use any Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 14-15:12.\nJoab arranged Absalom's return to Israel and Absalom conspired to be king.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"14-15:12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_21_6","questionText":"6. How did David's reluctance to act complicate his decisions and conflicts among his children?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_21_7","questionText":"7. What does Absalom's strategy to become king reveal about him?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_21_8","questionText":"8. How do you deal with difficult decisions and potential conflicts? How might you respond differently in the future?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 15:13-16:14 and Psalm 3.\nDavid abandoned Jerusalem and endured betrayal and ridicule.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"15:13-16:14"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"3:1-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_21_9","questionText":"9. Why did David choose to leave Jerusalem? What do you learn about David from his interactions with people along the journey?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_21_10","questionText":"10. Describe what David did and how he must have felt when he learned his trusted advisor, Ahithophel, joined Absalom? (See Psalm 41:7-9.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"41:7-9"}]},{"id":"2018_21_11","questionText":"11. Describe David's submission to and trust in God. Which truths are comforting to you? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 16:15-18:33.\nAbsalom's attempt to kill David resulted in his own death.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"16:15-18:33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_21_12","questionText":"12. From 2 Samuel 16:15-23, how were Nathan's words fulfilled through Ahithophel's advice? (See 2 Samuel 12:11-12.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"16:15-23"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"12:11-12"}]},{"id":"2018_21_13","questionText":"13. From 2 Samuel 17:1-23, how was David's prayer answered? (See 2 Samuel 15:31.) What do you learn about God's prophecies and/or prayer?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"17:1-23"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"15:31"}]},{"id":"2018_21_14","questionText":"14. What was David's response at the news of Absalom's death? What might have been going through his mind and heart?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 13-18 and Psalm 3.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"13:1-18:33"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"3:1-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_21_15","questionText":"15. What attribute of God resonated most from your study of this week's passage? How do you see that attribute displayed in the world today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_22?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_22","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"But you, Lord, are a shield around me, my glory, the One who lifts my head high.\" – Psalm 3:3","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_22_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_22_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 2 Samuel 19-20.\nDavid faced challenging decisions as he returned to rule Israel as king.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"19:1-20:26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_22_3","questionText":"3. Describe David's reaction to Absalom's death. How do you assess Joab's advice to David?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_22_4","questionText":"4. Consider the friends and foes David encountered as he returned and settled in Jerusalem. What do you learn about David? What do you learn about David's view of God and others?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_22_5","questionText":"5. How does this passage encourage or embolden you in your present circumstances? How will you respond?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 2 Samuel 21-22.\nDavid sought God's wisdom, battled his enemies and celebrated God's kindness.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"21:1-22:51"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_22_6","questionText":"6. What does David's encounter with the Gibeonites teach you about sin, restitution and God? (See Joshua 9:15.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Joshua","verse":"9:15"}]},{"id":"2018_22_7","questionText":"7. From 2 Samuel 22, what do the words and images say about David's relationship with and attitude toward God? What words describe God's kindness toward David?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"22:1-51"}]},{"id":"2018_22_8","questionText":"8. Which verses help, encourage or inspire you to worship? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 23.\nDavid celebrated God's gracious provision and victory through his mighty men.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"23:1-39"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_22_9","questionText":"9. What do David's last words reveal about his understanding of God's work in his life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_22_10","questionText":"10. How did David's men show bravery and loyalty to him? How will you demonstrate sacrificial love and loyalty at work, church and/or in your home?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_22_11","questionText":"11. In 2 Samuel 22, David credits God for his victories. How do you reconcile the heroic acts of David's mighty men with 2 Samuel 22? What do these two chapters teach you about the victorious Christian life?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"22:1-51"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"22:1-51"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 2 Samuel 24 with 1 Chronicles 21.\nDavid's census resulted in a deadly plague and costly sacrifice.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"24:1-25"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"21:1-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_22_12","questionText":"12. How might David have sinned in taking the census? (Use Exodus 30:12; James 1:13-16 or any other Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"30:12"},{"book":"James","verse":"1:13-16"}]},{"id":"2018_22_13","questionText":"13. What do you learn about God's judgment and mercy in response to the census? How have you experienced God's judgment and mercy?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_22_14","questionText":"14. How did David demonstrate reverence for God? How do you see God's people demonstrating reverence to God in your culture?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 2 Samuel 19-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"19:1-24:25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_22_15","questionText":"15. How did this week's study week impact your thinking about unity – within your family, church, community or nation?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_23?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_23","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"For who is God besides the Lord? And who is the Rock except our God? It is God who arms me with strength and keeps my way secure.\" – 2 Samuel 22:32-33","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_23_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Kings 1:1-27.\nNathan and Bathsheba exposed Adonijah's attempt to become Israel's king.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"1:1-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_23_3","questionText":"3. What stands out concerning Adonijah's strategy to gain the throne? How did he take advantage of circumstances and gain the favor of others?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_4a","questionText":"4. a. What was King David's responsibility in this situation? As the prophet, what was Nathan's responsibility?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_4b","questionText":"4. b. What God-given responsibility presently requires your attention and action?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_5","questionText":"5. Where and with whom is God inviting you to step out and exercise the influence He has given you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Kings 1:28-53.\nDavid declared Solomon Israel's next king.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"1:28-53"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_23_6","questionText":"6. What lessons do you learn from David's actions? How might those lessons also apply in your circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_7","questionText":"7. What was Jonathan's message, and what were the implications? Why did Adonijah's guests respond as they did?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_8","questionText":"8. Describe Solomon's response to Adonijah. Which qualities will you ask God to develop in you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Chronicles 22:1-19; 29:1-20.\nDavid made extensive preparations for the temple before his death.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"22:1-19"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"29:1-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_23_9","questionText":"9. What was most meaningful to you in David's charge and prayers for Solomon? How might you similarly encourage and/or pray for someone else?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_10","questionText":"10. What do David's words and actions reveal about his belief in God? How do these truths about God encourage you in your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_11","questionText":"11. How has or will David's views on giving impact the way you give?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 2 with 1 Chronicles 29:21-25.\nSolomon received and acted on David's instructions.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"2:1-46"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"29:21-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_23_12","questionText":"12. What spiritual and practical counsel did David give Solomon?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_13","questionText":"13. What determines when and how you respond to counsel from others?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_23_14","questionText":"14. What were the results of Solomon's response to David's instructions? What spiritual and practical lessons do you learn about work God entrusts to people? (See 1 Kings 2:12, 46.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"2:12"},{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"2:46"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 1-2 with 1 Chronicles 22, 29.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"1:1-2:46"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"22:1-19"},{"book":"1 Chronicles","verse":"29:1-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_23_15","questionText":"15. How did this week's study impact the influence you desire to have on and the legacy you want to leave to others (family, church, community, etc.)?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_24?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_24","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Since my youth, God, you have taught me, and to this day I declare your marvelous deeds.\" – Psalm 71:17","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_24_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_24_2","questionText":"2. What from the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study impacted you most in the past week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Kings 3:1-4; 2 Chronicles 1:1-6; Deuteronomy 17:16-20.\nSolomon loved the Lord but sacrificed on the high places.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"3:1-4"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"1:1-6"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"17:16-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_24_3","questionText":"3. Describe Solomon's actions in view of God's instructions in Deuteronomy 17:16-20.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"17:16-20"}]},{"id":"2018_24_4","questionText":"4. Give examples of actions you or your culture may applaud but that may trap or mislead God's people.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_24_5","questionText":"5. From the Deuteronomy passage, what were some of the good purposes behind God's instructions? How have God's instructions protected or blessed you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Kings 3:5-28; 2 Chronicles 1:7-13; Proverbs 1.\nSolomon asked for and applied his God-given wisdom.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"3:5-28"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"1:7-13"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"1:1-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_24_6","questionText":"6. How did Solomon respond to God's gracious invitation? What do you learn about Solomon from his request?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_24_7","questionText":"7. How did God respond to Solomon's request? What do you learn about God from His answer?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_24_8","questionText":"8. What does Proverbs 1 teach about becoming wise? How will you apply what you are learning?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"1:1-32"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 4:1-28; 2 Chronicles 1:14-17.\nSolomon established Israel's government and ruled in peace and prosperity.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"4:1-28"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"1:14-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_24_9","questionText":"9. How did Solomon show discernment in the practical ways he governed Israel? What can and will you apply in your home or workplace?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_24_10","questionText":"10. How did the nation of Israel benefit under Solomon's rule? (See Ecclesiastes 3:10-14; 5:18-20.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"3:10-14"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"5:18-20"}]},{"id":"2018_24_11","questionText":"11. What are some potential temptations and distractions that arise during times of prosperity and ease? How will you guard against those that particularly tempt or distract you? (See Deuteronomy 8:10-18; 17:16-17.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"8:10-18"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"17:16-17"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 4:29-34.\nSolomon's wisdom surpassed all others.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"4:29-34"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_24_12","questionText":"12. How do these verses show God fulfilled His promises to Solomon? (See 1 Kings 3:10-15.) How does this encourage you as you wait on God to fulfill His promises today?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"3:10-15"}]},{"id":"2018_24_13","questionText":"13. What stands out to you about Solomon's God-given wisdom? How does Solomon's experience demonstrate the way God gives supreme wisdom? (See 1 Corinthians 1: 18-25; James 1:5; 3:13-17 or any other Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"1:"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"18:1-25:undefined"},{"book":"James","verse":"1:5"},{"book":"James","verse":"3:13-17"}]},{"id":"2018_24_14","questionText":"14. What had Solomon learned about wisdom? In what ways have you experienced what Solomon says about wisdom? (See Ecclesiastes 1:16-18; 2:13; 4:13; 8:1.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"1:16-18"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"2:13"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"4:13"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"8:1"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Kings 3-4; 2 Chronicles 1; and Proverbs 1.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"3:1-4:34"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"1:1-17"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"1:1-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_24_15","questionText":"15. How did this week's study impact your thinking about God's wisdom vs. the world's wisdom?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_24_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: 1 Kings 3-4.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"3:1-4:34"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_25?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_25","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge, but fools despise wisdom and instruction.\" – Proverbs 1:7","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.\nUse this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)\nFrom the past week's study, what made the most significant impact on you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","questions":[]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Proverbs 1.\nProverbs 1-9 offer advice godly parents and mentors can pass on to others.","readVerse":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"1:1-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_25_3","questionText":"3. Explain Proverbs 1:7 in your own words. What does it mean to \"fear the Lord\"?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"1:7"}]},{"id":"2018_25_4","questionText":"4. What are some of the benefits of wisdom? Which one is most relevant or comforting to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_25_5","questionText":"5. Skim Proverbs 2-3 to note a few warnings and commands that stand out to you. Which one calls you to change your response to a current circumstance?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"2:1-3:35"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Proverbs 14 and 16.\nProverbs 10:1-22:16 describe growth in wise living and the costs of foolishness.","readVerse":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"14:1-35"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"16:1-33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_25_6","questionText":"6. How does Proverbs 14 describe a wise person? Which characteristics would you like God to grow in you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"14:1-35"}]},{"id":"2018_25_7","questionText":"7. What does Proverbs 14 reveal about God? What truth comforts or challenges you most?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"14:1-35"}]},{"id":"2018_25_8","questionText":"8. What truths does Proverbs 16 reveal about speech? How will you practice wise speech in your home, friendships, church and workplace?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"16:1-33"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Proverbs 28 and 29.\nProverbs 22:17-29:27 describe good citizenship for community and family life.","readVerse":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"28:1-28"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"29:1-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_25_9","questionText":"9. Which verses about leadership (rulers) will you apply? How?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_25_10","questionText":"10. Which verses about wealth and poverty will you put into practice? How?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_25_11","questionText":"11. What did you learn about righteous and wicked living? How do these verses challenge or comfort you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Proverbs 30-31.\nProverbs 30-31 describe observing wisdom in action to learn from others.","readVerse":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"30:1-31:31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_25_12","questionText":"12. From Proverbs 30, what observations about nature and life are most practical to you? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"30:1-33"}]},{"id":"2018_25_13a","questionText":"13. a. Proverbs 31 personifies wisdom as \"the wife of noble character.\" What aspects of this ideal image stand out to you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"31:1-31"}]},{"id":"2018_25_13b","questionText":"13. b. How do these descriptions help you recognize wisdom in others and call you to become a wiser member in your family and church?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_25_14","questionText":"14. Which of these verses will you share with those who have been entrusted to your care?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Proverbs 1, 14, 16, 28, 29, 30, 31.","readVerse":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"1:1-32"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"14:1-35"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"16:1-33"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"28:1-28"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"29:1-27"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"30:1-33"},{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"31:1-31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_25_15","questionText":"15. Choose a few verses from this lesson and think about how the truths line up with your daily actions. Where do you see yourself living out these verses? Where do you see a need for change? Share with your group what God's Word has revealed to you.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_26?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_26","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Trust in the Lord with all your heart and lean not on your own understanding; in all your ways submit to him, and he will make your paths straight.\" – Proverbs 3:5-6","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.\nUse this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","questions":[{"id":"2018_26_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Kings 5:1-6.\nSolomon asked the king of Tyre for resources to build God's temple.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"5:1-6"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_26_3","questionText":"3. What did Solomon plan to do as king? What opportunities did Solomon see and seize?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_26_4","questionText":"4. Describe how God made advance preparations before Solomon initiated building the temple. How did circumstances confirm the timing of Solomon's desire?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_26_5","questionText":"5. How are you, or will you, take initiative in the work God has given you? Where is God inviting you to trust Him?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Kings 5:7-18.\nSolomon assembled the resources and labor to build the temple.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"5:7-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_26_6","questionText":"6. How did Solomon use his wisdom, influence and resources to implement and accomplish this massive undertaking? What stands out in the negotiations and agreement between Solomon and Hiram? (2 Chronicles 2 provides additional details.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"2:1-18"}]},{"id":"2018_26_7","questionText":"7. What thoughts or questions did you have regarding Solomon's use of conscripted Israelite labor and enslavement of foreigners? (Use 1 Kings 9:20-22, 2 Chronicles 2:17-18 or any passage of Scripture.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"9:20-22"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"2:17-18"}]},{"id":"2018_26_8","questionText":"8. What desire or opportunity has God given you that appears to be greater than your ability? How do God's dealings with Solomon encourage you to go forward in obedience?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 6:1-13.\nGod gave promises to Solomon while he was building the temple.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"6:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_26_9","questionText":"9. What other events occurred in the Mount Moriah region? What connections do you see between these events and the temple? (See Genesis 22:1-18; 2 Samuel 24:18-25; 2 Chronicles 3:1 and any other reference in Scripture.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"22:1-18"},{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"24:18-25"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"3:1"}]},{"id":"2018_26_10","questionText":"10. What promises did God make to Solomon as he built the temple? Why would God give this message at this particular time?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_26_11","questionText":"11. How does God help you prioritize your relationship with Him during the daily work and demands of life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 6:14-38.\nSolomon completed the temple.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"6:14-38"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_26_12","questionText":"12. What were Solomon's goals in building the temple? Why? (See 2 Chronicles 2:4-9.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"2:4-9"}]},{"id":"2018_26_13","questionText":"13. What stands out to you in the temple construction and completion? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_26_14","questionText":"14. How does a person work and serve in a way that reflects the greatness of God instead of the worker? How might you need to adjust your work and service to better reflect God's greatness?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Kings 5-6 and 2 Chronicles 2-3.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"5:1-6:38"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"2:1-3:17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_26_15","questionText":"15. What was your biggest lesson learned from your personal study this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_27?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_27","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"And I will live among the Israelites and will not abandon my people Israel.\" – 1 Kings 6:13","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_27_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_27_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Kings 7:1-51.\nSolomon constructed his palace and commissioned the temple furnishings.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"7:1-51"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_27_3","questionText":"3. Why does Scripture mention the time Solomon spent building the temple and the palace at this point? What are some possible lessons?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_27_4","questionText":"4. How was Huram described? How does this affect your thinking about different ways to serve God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_27_5","questionText":"5. What was the purpose of the temple vessels and furnishings in Solomon's day? To whom did they point? (Use 2 Chronicles 4; Hebrews 9:1-23; Revelation 21:22-22:5 or any other reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"4:1-22"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"9:1-23"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"21:22-22:5"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Kings 8:1-11.\nThe priests brought the ark of the covenant to the Most Holy Place.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"8:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_27_6","questionText":"6. What did the ark of the covenant signify? What is meaningful to you about the ark's transport and placement? (Use Exodus 25:22; 1 Samuel 4:21-22; 6:1-21 or any other reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"25:22"},{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"4:21-22"},{"book":"1 Samuel","verse":"6:1-21"}]},{"id":"2018_27_7","questionText":"7. How does God dwell among people today? How can you be sure God dwells in you? (Use John 10:29; 2 Corinthians 6:16 or any other reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"10:29"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"6:16"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 8:11-21.\nThe dark cloud filled God's temple.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"8:11-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_27_8","questionText":"8. Who and what did the dark cloud that filled the temple represent? (See Exodus 24:15-18; 33:7-11.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"24:15-18"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"33:7-11"}]},{"id":"2018_27_9","questionText":"9. Where and how is the Lord's glory seen since the days of Jesus Christ? (See Psalm 19; Acts 2; 2 Corinthians 3:17-18 or any other reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"19:1-14"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"2:1-47"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"3:17-18"}]},{"id":"2018_27_10","questionText":"10. What opportunities is God giving you to reflect His character?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_27_11","questionText":"11. Solomon celebrated and told others of God's faithfulness to keep His promises. How will you do the same thing?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 8:22-66.\nSolomon prayed and dedicated the temple.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"8:22-66"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_27_12","questionText":"12. What did Solomon's prayer reveal about his understanding of and belief about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_27_13","questionText":"13. What did Solomon's prayer reveal about his understanding of and belief about the nation of Israel, and all mankind?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_27_14","questionText":"14. How might Solomon's prayer affect the way you pray? What will you put into practice?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Kings 7-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"7:1-8:66"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_27_15","questionText":"15. What did you learn about God? What did you learn about yourself?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_28?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_28","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Lord, the God of Israel, there is no God like you in heaven above or on earth below--you who keep your covenant of love with your servants who continue wholeheartedly in your way.\" – 1 Kings 8:23","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.\nUse this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)\nFrom the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","questions":[]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Kings 9:1-9.\nThe Lord appeared to Solomon a second time.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"9:1-9"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_28_3","questionText":"3. What had Solomon accomplished at the point the Lord appeared to him a second time? (1 Kings 4:24-34)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"4:24-34"}]},{"id":"2018_28_4","questionText":"4. What warnings and promises did God make to Solomon? What was the point of these words?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_28_5","questionText":"5. What does it look like to \"walk faithfully with integrity of heart and uprightness\"? How is this reminder relevant in your current circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Kings 9:10-28; 2 Chronicles 8.\nSolomon built his kingdom.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"9:10-28"},{"book":"2 Chronicles","verse":"8:1-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_28_6","questionText":"6. What was the focus of Solomon's time and energy during these years?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_28_7","questionText":"7. How did Solomon demonstrate both wisdom and questionable judgment?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_28_8","questionText":"8. What does the way you spend your time and energy say about you? How do you measure the success of a pursuit?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 10:1-13.\nThe Queen of Sheba visited Solomon.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"10:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_28_9","questionText":"9. What drew the Queen of Sheba to Solomon? Once she met him, what impressed the Queen of Sheba about Solomon?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_28_10","questionText":"10. What conclusion did the Queen of Sheba make about having a ruler who applies godly wisdom? What conclusion did she make about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_28_11","questionText":"11. Compare the similarities and differences between King Solomon and King Jesus. Perhaps you are wondering if Jesus is all that He claims to be. What hard questions would you like to ask Jesus? (Use any reference in Scripture.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 10:14-29; Psalm 72.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"10:14-29"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"72:1-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_28_12","questionText":"12. Psalm 72 is a prayer of David for his son Solomon. How was this prayer answered through Solomon's life? For whom does this encourage you to pray?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"72:1-20"}]},{"id":"2018_28_13","questionText":"13. What does Solomon's experience reveal about the blessings and challenges of great wealth and talent? What is the lesson for you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Kings 9-10; Psalm 72","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"9:1-10:29"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"72:1-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_28_14","questionText":"14. What is the most important or challenging thing you learned this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_28_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: 1 Kings 9-10.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"9:1-10:29"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_29?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_29","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Because of the Lord's eternal love for Israel, he has made you king to maintain justice and righteousness.\" – 1 Kings 10:9b","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2018_29_1","questionText":"1. Use this space to record how you have seen God's activity during the week. (How has He provided, answered, comforted, reconciled, guided, etc.?)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_29_2","questionText":"2. From the past week's study, what made the most significant impact to you in the notes, lecture, group sharing or personal study?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read 1 Kings 11:1-8.\nSolomon loved forbidden women and worshipped false gods.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"11:1-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_29_3","questionText":"3. What commands did Solomon disobey? (See Exodus 34:11-17; Deuteronomy 17:16-17 or any other Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"34:11-17"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"17:16-17"}]},{"id":"2018_29_4","questionText":"4. Why does God set boundaries around marriage? How are God's boundaries for marriage for the good of His children, then and now?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_29_5","questionText":"5. How do you proceed when God's commands come into conflict with your decisions and desires?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read 1 Kings 11:9-13.\nGod promised to divide the kingdom because of Solomon's disobedience.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"11:9-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_29_6","questionText":"6. Why was God angry with Solomon? Why does God command our undivided worship? (Use Psalm 16:11; Ecclesiastes 2:1-10; Isaiah 45:5-6; 46:3-10; Acts 17:25 or any Scripture reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"16:11"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"2:1-10"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"45:5-6"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"46:3-10"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"17:25"}]},{"id":"2018_29_7","questionText":"7. Solomon attempted to worship God and idols. What are some present-day examples of idolatry? What in your life might be an idol?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_29_8","questionText":"8. What consequences did God promise would come to Solomon and his kingdom? What do you learn about God's timing, justice and mercy?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 11:14-26.\nGod raised up adversaries against Solomon.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"11:14-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_29_9","questionText":"9. Describe the adversaries God \"raised up\" against Solomon. How did God demonstrate faithfulness to His promises? (See 1 Kings 6:12; 9:3-9)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"6:12"},{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"9:3-9"}]},{"id":"2018_29_10","questionText":"10. What are the opposing forces God's people face today? (For help, see John 15:18-21; Ephesians 6:12; 1 Peter 5:8; James 1:13-14; 1 John 2:16.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"15:18-21"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"6:12"},{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"5:8"},{"book":"James","verse":"1:13-14"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"2:16"}]},{"id":"2018_29_11","questionText":"11. What is your first response when hardship and adversaries arise? How has God used opposition and hardship to turn your heart and attention back to Him?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read 1 Kings 11:26-43; Ecclesiastes 9:12; 12:1-14.\nJeroboam learned God's intent to give him 10 tribes.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"11:26-43"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"9:12"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"12:1-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_29_12","questionText":"12. What did the Lord promise Jeroboam? What were the conditions?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_29_13","questionText":"13. What can you infer about Solomon's last months of life? Why did he summarize life as he did? (See Ecclesiastes 9:12; 12:1-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"9:12"},{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"12:1-14"}]},{"id":"2018_29_14","questionText":"14. As you reflect back over Solomon's life, what lessons do you want to remember? How will they shape the way you live?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review 1 Kings 11.","readVerse":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"11:1-43"}],"questions":[{"id":"2018_29_15","questionText":"15. What attribute of God resonated most from your study of this week's passage? How do you see that attribute displayed in the world today?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2018_29_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: 1 Kings 11.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Kings","verse":"11:1-43"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2018_30?lang=eng":{"id":"2018_30","name":"","memoryVerse":"\"Many are the plans in a person's heart, but it is the Lord's purpose that prevails.\" – Proverbs 19:21","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2018_30_1","questionText":"1. What did you learn about God through the study of People of the Promised Land I, and what difference has that made in your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2018_30_2","questionText":"2. What did you learn about yourself during the study, and how did God use that to draw you closer to Him?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2018_30_3","questionText":"3. In what ways did you experience God changing your thoughts, attitudes, desires and actions this year? How did you see Him work in the lives of the children you bring to BSF?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2018_30_4","questionText":"4. How has your relationship with Jesus Christ changed this year, and what impact has that had on your relationships with others?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2018_30_5","questionText":"5. Now that you have completed the study of People of the Promised Land I, what do you think God's plan for you includes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2018_30_6","questionText":"6. What do you want to tell others about God's work in your life during the study of People of the Promised Land I? Who might need that encouragement to trust Jesus at this time?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_1?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_1","name":"Romans2017_1","memoryVerse":"“For I am not ashamed of the gospel, because it is the power of God that brings salvation to everyone who believes: first to the Jew, then to the Gentile.” – Romans 1:16 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_1_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 1:1-7.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:1-7"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_3","questionText":"3. What do you learn about Paul from his introduction? (See also Acts 9:1-21; 1 Timothy 1:12-16.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"9:1-21"},{"book":"1 Timothy","verse":"1:12-16"}]},{"id":"2017_1_4","questionText":"4. The word “gospel” means “good news.” What news do these verses announce, why is it good, and how have you experienced this goodness? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_5","questionText":"5. How did Paul describe the Roman Christians, what did he offer them, and how do his words affect your attitude about yourself or other believers? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 1:8-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:8-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_6","questionText":"6. Whom did Paul thank, and why was he grateful?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_7","questionText":"7. What do you learn about the relationship between serving God and prayer? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_8a","questionText":"8. a.  For what specifically did Paul pray, and how did God answer Paul’s prayer? (See Acts 28:14-20,30-31.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"28:14-20"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"28:30-31"}]},{"id":"2017_1_8b","questionText":"8. b. What do you learn about God from Paul’s prayers, and for whom or for what does this encourage you to pray?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 1:11-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:11-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_9","questionText":"9. Why did Paul want to come to the Roman church, and why had he not come previously?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_10","questionText":"10.  How could Paul’s example help you when you face obstacles in serving God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_11","questionText":"11. Why was Paul obligated to all people, and what was his attitude toward his obligation? What is your attitude toward your obligation to share your knowledge of Jesus with others? (See also Acts 26:11-18.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"26:11-18"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 1:16-17. Note: These verses are the theme of the entire book of Romans.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:16-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_12","questionText":"12. List reasons Paul was not ashamed of the gospel. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_13","questionText":"13. In what situations are you tempted to be ashamed of the gospel, and how could Paul’s reasons help you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_14","questionText":"14. How do these verses relate to your personal experience of the gospel, and how are they also Paul’s personal  testimony? (See Philippians 3:4-9.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:4-9"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 1:1-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_15","questionText":"15.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_2?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_2","name":"Romans2017_2","memoryVerse":"“For in the gospel the righteousness of God is revealed – a righteousness that is by faith from first to last, just as it is written: ‘The righteous will live by faith.’ ” – Romans 1:17 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_2_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 1:18-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:18-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_3","questionText":"3.  Define the word “wrath,” and explain from these verses why God is revealing His wrath at the present time. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_4a","questionText":"4. a.  What can we learn about God from the natural world, and how can this encourage your own personal worship and conversations with unbelievers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_4b","questionText":"4. b.  What can we not learn about God from nature, and how may we learn these necessary truths?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_5","questionText":"5.  Define the word “suppress.” What results of suppressing the truth do you see in your own life and what will you ask God to help you do about it? How might that impact others who suppress the truth?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 1:21-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:21-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_6","questionText":"6.  From these verses, how has humanity rejected the knowledge of God that His creation reveals?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_7a","questionText":"7. a.  What is the first result of rejecting God, and why is this consequence appropriate?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_7b","questionText":"7. b.  What has God done about light in a dark world, and how can you bring God’s light to those around you who live in darkness? (See also John 1:4-9; 8:12; Matthew 5:14-16.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"1:4-9"},{"book":"John","verse":"8:12"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"5:14-16"}]},{"id":"2017_2_8","questionText":"8.  In verses 22-23, what exchange has humanity made, and how do these verses, as well as today’s world, show this exchange leads to degrading practices? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 1:24-28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:24-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_9a","questionText":"9. a.  What truth about God do these verses indicate humanity has exchanged for a lie?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_9b","questionText":"9. b.  What substitutes for God could you be worshipping or serving, and how would your life be impacted if God removed those substitutes?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_10","questionText":"10.  What are some of the reasons God links the sin of idolatry to sexual immorality? (See Genesis 1:26-27; 2:24-25; Mark 10:8-9; 1 Corinthians 6:9-11, 18-20.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"1:26-27"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"2:24-25"},{"book":"Mark","verse":"10:8-9"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"6:9-11"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"6:18-20"}]},{"id":"2017_2_11","questionText":"11.  What phrase occurs three times to describe God’s action, and how does this repeated phrase change your thoughts about those who seem to get away with immorality and injustice?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 1:28-32.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:28-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_12","questionText":"12.  How is a “depraved” mind different from one that does “not think it worthwhile to retain knowledge of God”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_13","questionText":"13.  Share how God has changed your thinking about a sin of which you previously approved.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 1:18-32.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:18-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_14","questionText":"14.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_3?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_3","name":"Romans2017_3","memoryVerse":"“For since the creation of the world, God’s invisible qualities – his eternal power and divine nature – have been clearly seen, being understood from what has been made, so that people are without excuse.” – Romans 1:20 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_3_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 2:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_3","questionText":"3. Why are the people in this passage without excuse, and upon what does God base His judgment?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_4","questionText":"4. What does it mean to pass judgment, and how does this differ from knowing and teaching God’s standards? Tell how you struggle with passing judgment on others.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_5","questionText":"5. How has God showered you with kindness and patience, and how do you demonstrate these godly attributes toward others?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 2:5-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:5-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_6","questionText":"6. What do stubborn, unrepentant people store up for themselves, and what are you storing up? (See also Matthew 6:19-20; 12:35.)  ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"6:19-20"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"12:35"}]},{"id":"2017_3_7a","questionText":"7. a. From verses 7-11, list the results when people follow the path of good and when they follow the path of evil.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_7b","questionText":"7. b. What do your actions reveal about your heart attitude toward God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_8","questionText":"8. What standard will God use to judge people’s obedience?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 2:17-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:17-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_9a","questionText":"9. a. What privileges did God give the Jews, and what was their attitude toward their privileges?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_9b","questionText":"9. b.  What specific privileges has He given you, and how do you sometimes demonstrate the same attitude?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_10","questionText":"10. Which of the 10 Commandments did Paul accuse the Jews of breaking? List some common ways Christians who teach others about following Jesus fail to do what He says? (See Exodus 20:1-17; Matthew 7:21-23.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"20:1-17"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"7:21-23"}]},{"id":"2017_3_11","questionText":"11. What happens when any religious person violates the standards they proclaim? Is there an area of your life in which you may be guilty of this?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 2:25-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:25-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_12a","questionText":"12. a. What is circumcision, and why would this sign be a source of pride? (See Genesis 17:1-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:1-14"}]},{"id":"2017_3_12b","questionText":"12. b. Name some outward signs people today rely on to be in right relationship with God.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_13","questionText":"13. According to this passage, what is a true Jew, and what does this mean to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 2.","questions":[{"id":"2017_3_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_4?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_4","name":"Romans2017_4","memoryVerse":"“For God does not show favoritism.” – Romans 2:11","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_4_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 3:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_3a","questionText":"3. a. What expectations might the Jews in Paul’s day have had about their spiritual advantages? (See also Romans 2:6-29.) What expectations of God do you have concerning any spiritual advantages you may have?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:6-29"}]},{"id":"2017_4_3b","questionText":"3. b. Why was it an advantage for the Jews that God entrusted them with His very words, and how is God’s Word, the Bible, a great advantage for you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_4","questionText":"4. Try to connect the promises God made to the Jews with Romans 3:3-4. (Some of the promises are found in Genesis 12:1-7; Deuteronomy 30:15-20; Jeremiah 31:35-37. There are several interpretations.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:3-4"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"12:1-7"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"30:15-20"},{"book":"Jeremiah","verse":"31:35-37"}]},{"id":"2017_4_5","questionText":"5. Ultimately, who is responsible for a person’s sin and unbelief? Why? (See Psalm 51:1-6; James 1:13-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"51:1-6"},{"book":"James","verse":"1:13-14"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 3:5-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:5-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_6","questionText":"6.  What “human argument” did Paul expose as wrong, and why was God’s wrath justified?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_7","questionText":"7. What should be the believer’s attitude toward sin, and how does your attitude toward sin compare with your  actions? (Use any Bible passages you wish to support your answer.) ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 3:9-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:9-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_8a","questionText":"8. a. From these verses, what are the promised effects of sin, and how have you seen these effects in your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_8b","questionText":"8. b. What words in verse 13-14 reveal how seriously God views our speech? What warning do you receive about your words, and what specifically will you ask God to help you change? (See also James 3:5-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"James","verse":"3:5-10"}]},{"id":"2017_4_9","questionText":"9. According to verse 18, what sin appears to underlie the sins in verses 13-17, and how does this passage show this root sin is true of people in both Old and New Testament times?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_10","questionText":"10.  What does it look like to fear (have a reverent awe for) God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 3:19-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:19-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_11","questionText":"11. What does Paul conclude in verses 19-20?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_12a","questionText":"12. a. What does it mean to have every mouth silenced and the whole world accountable to God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_12b","questionText":"12. b. How has the study of Romans helped you to identify, confess and repent of your sin?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 3:1-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:1-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_13","questionText":"13.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_5?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_5","name":"Romans2017_5","memoryVerse":"“As it is written: ‘There is no one righteous, not even one; there is no one who understands; there is no one who seeks God.’ ” – Romans 3:10-11","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_5_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 3:21-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:21-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_3","questionText":"3.  Define “righteousness.” Where does it come from, and how is it received? How does this compare with your  understanding of righteousness?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_4","questionText":"4.  What does “apart from the law” mean? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_5a","questionText":"5. a.  How does the Old Testament also show the righteousness God gives is apart from the law? Why does this matter? (See Genesis 15:6; Jeremiah 31:33-34; Ezekiel 36:26-27 or any other Old Testament reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:6"},{"book":"Jeremiah","verse":"31:33-34"},{"book":"Ezekiel","verse":"36:26-27"}]},{"id":"2017_5_5b","questionText":"5. b.  Who may receive God’s righteousness, and what is your response to His gift? (See also Romans 10:9-10, 14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:9-10"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:14"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 3:23-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:23-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_6","questionText":"6.  What examples might you use from the Bible, history, current culture or your own life to help an unbeliever under-stand “all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_7a","questionText":"7. a.  Define “justified.” How is justification accomplished, and why is that good news? (See also Genesis 15:6; Isaiah 53:11; 2 Corinthians 5:21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:6"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"53:11"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"5:21"}]},{"id":"2017_5_7b","questionText":"7. b.  Explain “the redemption that came by Christ Jesus”. What does redemption teach you about God? (For additional help see Mark 10:45; Ephesians 1:7-8; Titus 2:14; 1 Peter 1:18)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Mark","verse":"10:45"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:7-8"},{"book":"Titus","verse":"2:14"},{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"1:18"}]},{"id":"2017_5_8","questionText":"8.  How does God’s grace in justification and redemption reveal that you are loved and wanted by God? How does that impact your response to Him? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 3:24-26.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:24-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_9","questionText":"9.  What does it mean that Jesus is a  “sacrifice of atonement” (“propitiation,” ESV)? How does this assure you that God’s justice has been satisfied? (For help see Hebrews 2:17; 1 John 2:2; 4:10; use a dictionary if you wish.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"2:17"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"2:2"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"4:10"}]},{"id":"2017_5_10","questionText":"10.  Why would God present His own Son as a sacrifice of atonement and how can you express your gratitude for such great love?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 3:25-26.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:25-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_11","questionText":"11.  How did God demonstrate His righteousness in Jesus Christ? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_12","questionText":"12.  How can you know you will never have to face God’s just punishment and with whom will you share the freedom this knowledge gives?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 3:21-26.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:21-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_13","questionText":"13.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_6?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_6","name":"Romans2017_6","memoryVerse":"“This righteousness is given through faith in Jesus Christ to all who believe. There is no difference between Jew and Gentile, for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God.” – Romans 3:22-23 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_6_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 3:27-28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:27-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_3","questionText":"3. How do people today boast about their spirituality or relationship with God, and why is all boasting to be excluded?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_4","questionText":"4. Name some different ways people try to justify themselves before God. Which one most accurately applies to the way you live?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_5","questionText":"5. What is wrong with people’s hearts and relationships when they boast of their own righteousness, and how can you guard against self-righteousness?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 3:27-28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:27-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_6","questionText":"6. List various ways people today understand and use the word “faith.” ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_7a","questionText":"7. a.  Read Hebrews 11. Describe in your own words the kind of faith that justifies or saves a person. (You may use any Scripture references to support your answer.) List some things these believers’ faith caused them to do.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"11:1-40"}]},{"id":"2017_6_7b","questionText":"7. b. Share something your faith has recently prompted you to do.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 3:29-30.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:29-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_8","questionText":"8.  Who are Gentiles, and why would Jews in Paul’s day look down on them? (See Romans 2:17, 23, 25. Use a  dictionary if necessary.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:17"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:23"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:25"}]},{"id":"2017_6_9","questionText":"9. How does the fact that “there is only one God” and one way of salvation compare with how many people  think today?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_10","questionText":"10. What truths from this passage or previous lessons could you use to respond graciously to people who say all  religions are true or there are many gods or many ways to God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 3:31.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_11","questionText":"11.  How does faith uphold the law? (See Exodus 20:1-17; Romans 8:3-4; 13:8-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"20:1-17"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:3-4"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:8-10"}]},{"id":"2017_6_12","questionText":"12. Give examples of what goes wrong when people in the church believe they do not need to obey God’s commands and also teach others to disobey. (This thinking is called “antinomianism.”) (See also Jude 1:4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Jude","verse":"1:4"}]},{"id":"2017_6_13","questionText":"13.  If  God has justified you through faith, give examples of how He encourages and enables you to obey Him.  (See Romans 8:12-17, 31-34; Philippians 2:12-13; 1 John 1:5-10.)  ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:12-17"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:31-34"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"2:12-13"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"1:5-10"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 3:27-31.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:27-31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_7?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_7","name":"Romans2017_7","memoryVerse":"“For we maintain that a person is justified by faith apart from the works of the law.” – Romans 3:28 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_7_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 4:1-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:1-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_3","questionText":"3. What did Abraham believe, and how did his life show his faith and honor God? (For additional help, see Genesis 12:1-9; 13:1-18; 15:1-6, 18; 17:1-10, 23.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"12:1-9"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"13:1-18"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:1-6"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:18"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:1-10"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:23"}]},{"id":"2017_7_4","questionText":"4. Why do workers not consider their wages a gift from their employers? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_5a","questionText":"5. a. What gift does God give all who trust Him, and what wages do people who insist on an employer-employee relationship with God earn? (See also Romans 6:23.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:23"}]},{"id":"2017_7_5b","questionText":"5. b. Which type of relationship with God do you have? What does your life reveal about your faith and expecta- tions of God?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 4:6-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:6-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_6","questionText":"6. How did David learn the truth he taught in Psalm 32, quoted in Romans 4:7-8? (See 2 Samuel 11-12; Psalm 32; 51.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"11:1-12:33"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"32:1-11"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"51:1-19"}]},{"id":"2017_7_7","questionText":"7. How could these verses help believers who struggle with guilt from past sins? (You may use other verses from Scripture.) ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_8","questionText":"8. Privately and specifically, name sins God has counted against Christ instead of you. Share with your group a time you experienced the joy of forgiveness and how you will express thankfulness to Christ for taking your sin and giving you His righteousness. (See also 2 Corinthians 5:19-21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"5:19-21"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 4:9-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:9-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_9","questionText":"9. About how long after God declared Abraham righteous did He give the sign of circumcision to Abraham and the Law to Abraham’s descendants? Why is this sequence of events important? (See Genesis 15:6, 13-18; 16:1-4, 16; 17:25-26; Galatians 3:15-18.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:6"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:13-18"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"16:1-4"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"16:16"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:25-26"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"3:15-18"}]},{"id":"2017_7_10a","questionText":"10. a. What happens when people depend on their own obedience or on signs, such as circumcision, baptism or the Lord’s Supper, as a measure of their righteousness? What is the value of obedience and signs?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_10b","questionText":"10. b. Briefly explain why you believe you are or are not righteous in God’s eyes.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 4:16-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:16-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_11","questionText":"11. From these verses, describe the faith of Abraham and explain who Abraham’s offspring are.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_12","questionText":"12. How did Abraham face the facts of his situation, and what happened to his faith as he waited for God to fulfill  His promise? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_13","questionText":"13. What difficult situation has God used or is using to strengthen your faith?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:1-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 4","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_8?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_8","name":"Romans2017_8","memoryVerse":"“Yet he did not waver through unbelief regarding the promise of God, but was strengthened in his faith and gave glory to God, being fully persuaded that God had power to do what he had promised.” – Romans 4:20-21 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_8_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 5:1-2.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:1-2"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_3","questionText":"3. What does it mean to have peace with God, and how is it accomplished? How is this different from and superior to peaceful circumstances or feelings? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_4","questionText":"4. What access do believers have through Jesus Christ, and how should this privilege impact your daily life? (See also John 14:6; Ephesians 2:18; 3:12; Hebrews 4:14-16.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"14:6"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:18"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"3:12"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"4:14-16"}]},{"id":"2017_8_5","questionText":"5. Christians will see God’s glory in heaven. How might focusing on your “hope of the glory of God” strengthen you, comfort you or give you joy today? (See also Psalm 17:15; Matthew 5:8; 1 John 3:2; Revelation 22:3-4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"17:15"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"5:8"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"3:2"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"22:3-4"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 5:3-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:3-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_6a","questionText":"6. a. Why and how can believers glory (rejoice or boast) in suffering?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_6b","questionText":"6. b.  How has God used your suffering to produce perseverance, character, hope and a deeper knowledge of His love in you and in those around you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_7","questionText":"7. Why does hope not disappoint us or “put us to shame,” and what role does the Holy Spirit play in this process? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 5:6-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:6-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_8a","questionText":"8. a. Give three words from these verses that describe the condition of those for whom Christ died. Why is this good news?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_8b","questionText":"8. b. How do these three words make clear that people cannot save themselves, and what is your personal experience of this? (See also Ephesians 2:1-9.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-9"}]},{"id":"2017_8_9","questionText":"9. How might these verses help you explain why Christianity is unique as compared with other religions and  philosophies?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 5:9-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:9-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_10","questionText":"10. List various aspects of salvation from these verses.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_11a","questionText":"11. a.  Define “reconciliation.” (If needed, use a dictionary.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_11b","questionText":"11. b.  Is God reconciled to us or are we reconciled to God, and what does it reveal about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_12","questionText":"12. How are we saved through Christ’s life, and what words or actions will you use to boast (rejoice) in Him?  (See also Romans 4:25; 6:8-10; 8:34; or other Bible passages you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:25"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:8-10"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:34"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 5:1-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_13","questionText":"13. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_14","questionText":"14. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 5:1-11","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:1-11"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_9?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_9","name":"Romans2017_9","memoryVerse":"“Therefore, since we have been justified through faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ.” –  Romans 5:1","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_9_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 5:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_3","questionText":"3.  Read Genesis 2:15-3:24. Who was the “one man” in Romans 5:12? What warning did God give him, and what harm did his sin cause? (See also Romans 3:9-11, 23; 8:20-21; 1 Corinthians 15:22; Ephesians 2:1-3.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"2:15-3:24"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:9-11"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:23"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:20-21"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"15:22"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-3"}]},{"id":"2017_9_4","questionText":"4. What do most people you know believe about humanity – that all people are born good, born neutral or born  sinners? What do you believe and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 5:14-19.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:14-19"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_5","questionText":"5. List ways Adam (“a pattern”) and Jesus Christ (“the one to come”) are the same and ways they differ. How did Jesus bring more good than all that Adam destroyed? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_6","questionText":"6. What is the “gift”? Why do verses 15-17 mention it so often, and what is your response to it?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_7","questionText":"7. What unites people to Adam, and what unites them to Christ? To whom are you united, and how do you know? (See also John 3:7-21; Romans 10:9-13; or other Bible passages.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"3:7-21"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:9-13"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 5:18-19.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:18-19"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_8","questionText":"8. What are some results of condemnation, and what impact do these verses have on you? (See Matthew 13:47-50;  Romans 2:8-9; Philippians 3:18-19; 2 Thessalonians 1:8-9; Revelation 20:14-15.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"13:47-50"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:8-9"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:18-19"},{"book":"2 Thessalonians","verse":"1:8-9"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"20:14-15"}]},{"id":"2017_9_9a","questionText":"9. a. What is the “one righteous act” that resulted in justification and life? (Use other verses if you wish.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_9b","questionText":"9. b. What are some results of life in Christ, and how are they evident in your life? (See John 10:28; Galatians 2:20; Ephesians 3:12; Philippians 3:20-21; Hebrews 13:20-21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"10:28"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"2:20"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"3:12"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:20-21"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"13:20-21"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 5:20-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:20-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_10a","questionText":"10. a. Why does law cause trespass (sin) to increase? (See Romans 7:7-12; Galatians 3:24.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:7-12"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"3:24"}]},{"id":"2017_9_10b","questionText":"10. b. How do you see this principle at work in you, your family, community or country?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_11","questionText":"11. Share briefly a recent example of God’s grace overcoming the consequences of your sin.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_12","questionText":"12. What are the two reigns (kingdoms) in verse 21, and what happens to those who belong to each kingdom? (See also Colossians 1:13-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Colossians","verse":"1:13-14"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 5:12-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_13","questionText":"13. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_14","questionText":"14. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 5:12-21","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-21"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_10?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_10","name":"Romans2017_10","memoryVerse":"“Consequently, just as one trespass resulted in condemnation for all people, so also one righteous act resulted in  justification and life for all people.” – Romans 5:18","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_10_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 6:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_3","questionText":"3. What thoughts in chapter 5 prompted Paul to ask the question in 6:1, and why? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_4","questionText":"4. What happens when Christians believe their sin does not matter? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_5","questionText":"5. When have you been tempted to sin because you knew God would forgive you? How might these verses strengthen you to fight sin instead?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 6:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_6","questionText":"6. Who are “we” and “us” in these verses?  If you are part of this group, rewrite verse 2 as your own statement. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_7","questionText":"7. Describe the spiritual reality to which water baptism points. (See also Acts 1:5; 2:38; 1 Corinthians 12:13;  Galatians 3:26-27; Colossians 2:11-12.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"1:5"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"2:38"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"12:13"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"3:26-27"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"2:11-12"}]},{"id":"2017_10_8","questionText":"8.  Specifically how does Paul say believers have died to sin?  If Christ is your Savior, how have you experienced this death personally and how are you now living a new life? (See also Romans 5:12-21; 2 Corinthians 5:14-21.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-21"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"5:14-21"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 6:5-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:5-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_9","questionText":"9. From these verses, name ways believers are united with Christ.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_10","questionText":"10. What does Paul mean by “the old self ”? (See also Ephesians 4:22-24; Colossians 3:9-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:22-24"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:9-10"}]},{"id":"2017_10_11","questionText":"11. For which aspects of your union with Christ will you thank God, and where do you need His help to believe He has set you free from sin? (See also Colossians 2:11-15.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Colossians","verse":"2:11-15"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 6:9-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:9-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_12","questionText":"12. List facts about Jesus from verses 9-10. How does verse 11 connect your life with what is true of Jesus?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_13","questionText":"13. What does it look like to be dead to sin but alive to Christ: In your home? In your school, workplace or community? In your church?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 6:1-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 6:1-11","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-11"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_11?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_11","name":"Romans2017_11","memoryVerse":"“In the same way, count yourselves dead to sin but alive to God in Christ Jesus.” – Romans 6:11 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_11_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 6:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_3","questionText":"3. What truths in earlier chapters of Romans precede the word “therefore” in verse 12? (See previous lessons.)  ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_4a","questionText":"4. a. List the two negative commands and the two positive commands, and explain why lasting change requires both negative and positive actions. (See also Ephesians 4:22-24; Colossians 3:9-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:22-24"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:9-10"}]},{"id":"2017_11_4b","questionText":"4. b.  Give specific ways you are tempted to offer any part of yourself to sin and ways to offer every part of yourself to God.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_5","questionText":"5. How does God’s promise in verse 14 encourage you in light of the commands in verses 12-13? (See also Romans 5:20-21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:20-21"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 6:15-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:15-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_6","questionText":"6. How do the questions in verses 1 and 15 differ, and how are they alike?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_7a","questionText":"7. a. What does it mean to “be a slave to sin” or a “slave to righteousness”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_7b","questionText":"7. b. Because we are slaves to the one we obey, would you describe yourself now as a slave to sin or a slave to righteousness, and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 6:17-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:17-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_8","questionText":"8. Compare and contrast obedience from the heart and following rules. Which describes your actions?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_9","questionText":"9. What is “the pattern of teaching” Paul says “claims the allegiance” of believers? (See Romans 6:1-14 or other Scripture passages.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-14"}]},{"id":"2017_11_10","questionText":"10. If Christ has set you free from sin, what are some aspects of your freedom for which you thank God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 6:19-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:19-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_11","questionText":"11. List ways in which people want to be free and why these things are or are not true freedom.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_12","questionText":"12. What are the results of being a slave to sin, and what are the results of being a slave to God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_13a","questionText":"13. a. How have you personally experienced sin’s wages, which lead to death? If you are a believer, how has God used those things for His glory and your good?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_13b","questionText":"13. b. What attitudes and behaviors are produced in you as you meditate on God’s gift of eternal life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 6:12-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:12-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 6:12-23","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:12-23"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_12?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_12","name":"Romans2017_12","memoryVerse":"“For the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.” – Romans 6:23 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_12_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 7:1-6.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:1-6"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_3","questionText":"3. How do these verses build on the truth of the believer’s union with Christ? (See Romans 6:1-11, 14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-11"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:14"}]},{"id":"2017_12_4a","questionText":"4. a. From what does Christ’s death free believers, to whom do they now belong and what is their purpose?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_4b","questionText":"4. b. If you are a believer, how are you living out your God-given purpose and freedom, especially in your relation- ships in work, family, community life, etc.?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_5","questionText":"5. Contrast “fruit for God” and “the new way of the Spirit” with “fruit for death” and “the old way of the written code.” (See also John 15:1-5 and Galatians 5:16-23.) Where do you see these patterns in your life? ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"15:1-5"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:16-23"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 7:7-13. Note: Christians differ about whether Romans 7:7-25 refers to Paul’s life before or after Jesus saved him.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:7-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_6","questionText":"6. From verses 7-13, what does the law do for people, and how does sin use the law against people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_7","questionText":"7. How does sin deceive you and harm your mind, emotions or body? What does sin reveal about your understanding of God and how will you respond to what He is showing you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 7:14-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:14-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_8","questionText":"8. Explain how the law is “spiritual” and why Paul describes himself as “unspiritual.”","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_9","questionText":"9. How would you explain Paul’s struggle in these verses to your family or others you want to help grow in Christ?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_10","questionText":"10. What do you do that you do not want to do, and what good do you not do that you really want to do?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 7:21-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:21-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_11","questionText":"11. Describe Paul’s distress over sin in these verses. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_12a","questionText":"12. a. How does Paul answer the question he asked in verse 24?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_12b","questionText":"12. b. Why is Paul’s answer the only true help for those who live under the burden of the law as well as those who tend to lawless living?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_13","questionText":"13. Can you share a time distress over sin led you to desperate prayer, and how might Romans 6 and 7 help you pray about your ongoing struggle with sin?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 7:1-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:1-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 7","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_13?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_13","name":"Romans2017_13","memoryVerse":"“What a wretched man I am! Who will rescue me from this body that is subject to death? Thanks be to God, who  delivers me through Jesus Christ our Lord!” – Romans 7:24-25a","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_13_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 8:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_3a","questionText":"3. a.  From your study of Romans 1-7, how would you explain Romans 8:1? What is the significance of “now” and “no condemnation”? (For additional help, see John 3:16-17; 5:24.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1"},{"book":"John","verse":"3:16-17"},{"book":"John","verse":"5:24"}]},{"id":"2017_13_3b","questionText":"3. b. How does Romans 8:1 affect the way you view yourself and others? What changes will you ask God to make in your thoughts or actions?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1"}]},{"id":"2017_13_4","questionText":"4.  How does this passage show that the whole Trinity (Father, Son and Holy Spirit) works to save sinners? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_5","questionText":"5.  Because those in Christ are no longer under law, why and how do they fulfill the law’s righteous requirements?  (See also John 14:15-21; 16:5-15.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"14:15-21"},{"book":"John","verse":"16:5-15"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 8:5-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:5-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_6","questionText":"6.  Name the two basic groups of people these verses describe and contrast their mindsets and lives.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_7","questionText":"7.  How can you recognize a mind set on what the Spirit desires? (See also Galatians 5:22-23; Colossians 3:1-4.) Would others say that is true of you? ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:22-23"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:1-4"}]},{"id":"2017_13_8","questionText":"8.  According to verses 9-11, what things are true of everyone in whom the Spirit of God (also called the Spirit of Christ) lives, and how do these truths encourage you today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 8:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_9","questionText":"9.  According to these verses, what is a Christian’s obligation and why? (See also 2 Corinthians 7:1; Philippians  3:10-14; 1 John 3:1-3.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"7:1"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:10-14"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"3:1-3"}]},{"id":"2017_13_10a","questionText":"10. a.  How can God’s children “put to death the misdeeds of the body”? (See also Galatians 5:13-26; Colossians 3:5-17.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:13-26"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:5-17"}]},{"id":"2017_13_10b","questionText":"10. b.  What does the phrase “put to death” teach about the attitude God’s children are to have toward their sin, and where do you need the Holy Spirit’s help to change your attitude and actions?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 8:14-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:14-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_11","questionText":"11.  List privileges of adoption into God’s family. (See also Romans 8:29.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29"}]},{"id":"2017_13_12","questionText":"12.   From the following verses, give additional benefits of being God’s child and, if you are a believer, express how you have experienced these benefits.  (Matthew 6:7-8; 10:29-31; Hebrews 12:7-11; 1 John 3:1-3) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"6:7-8"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"10:29-31"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"12:7-11"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"3:1-3"}]},{"id":"2017_13_13","questionText":"13.  How might these truths help you or others who struggle with doubt of God’s fatherly love?    ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 8:1-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_14","questionText":"14.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 8:1-17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1-17"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_14?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_14","name":"Romans2017_14","memoryVerse":"“Therefore, there is now no condemnation for those who are in Christ Jesus.” – Romans 8:1","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_14_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 8:17-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:17-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_3","questionText":"3. What was Paul’s experience with suffering, and how does this affect your understanding of these verses and encourage you in your suffering?  (See 2 Corinthians 4:7-18; 6:4-10; 11:23-28 or other verses you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"4:7-18"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"6:4-10"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"11:23-28"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4a","questionText":"4. a. What does the word “glory” mean? (Use a dictionary for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_4b","questionText":"4. b. Give various aspects of our “glory” from the following verses:  2 Corinthians 3:18","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"3:18"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4c","questionText":"4. b.  Philippians 3:20-21","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:20-21"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4d","questionText":"4. b.  Colossians 1:27","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Colossians","verse":"1:27"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4e","questionText":"4. b.  2 Thessalonians 2:13-14","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Thessalonians","verse":"2:13-14"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4f","questionText":"4. b.  Hebrews 2:10","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"2:10"}]},{"id":"2017_14_5","questionText":"5. What is the relationship between suffering and glory, and what hope does this give you for yourself, your church or for suffering believers worldwide?  (See references given above or other verses you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 8:19-22.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:19-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_6","questionText":"6. What does Paul mean by “creation” in this passage?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_7","questionText":"7. List ways you see the creation subject to frustration and decay today. (See also Genesis 1:27-2:1; 3:17-19.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"1:27-2:1"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"3:17-19"}]},{"id":"2017_14_8","questionText":"  8. When and how will creation be liberated? (See 2 Peter 3:13; Revelation 21:1 or other verses you may know.) How do these truths help you distinguish proper creation care from idolizing nature or trusting in people’s efforts to renew the planet?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Peter","verse":"3:13"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"21:1"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 8:23-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:23-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_9","questionText":"  9. Who and what groan in these verses, and why do they groan? (See also Romans 8:22, 26.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:22"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:26"}]},{"id":"2017_14_10a","questionText":"10. a. For what do Christians hope, and how are they to wait?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_10b","questionText":"10. b. For what are you waiting and hoping, and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 8:26-27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:26-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_11","questionText":"11. From these verses, share various ways the Holy Spirit works in a believer’s life and at least one way He has been working in yours. Romans 8:26-27","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:26-27"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11b","questionText":"11. Luke 12:12","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Luke","verse":"12:12"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11c","questionText":"11. Acts 1:8","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"1:8"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11d","questionText":"11. Acts 16:6-10; 20:22","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"16:6-10"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"20:22"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11e","questionText":"11. Ephesians 4:3-4","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:3-4"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11f","questionText":"11. Ephesians 6:17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"6:17"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11g","questionText":"11. 1 Corinthians 2:12","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"2:12"}]},{"id":"2017_14_12a","questionText":"12. a. What is meant by “the Spirit intercedes for God’s people in accordance with the will of God”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_12b","questionText":"12. b. Who, besides the Holy Spirit, intercedes for you today, and for whom do you pray? (See Romans 8:34 or  other verses you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:34"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 8:18-27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:18-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_13","questionText":"13. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_14","questionText":"14. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 8:18-27","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:18-27"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_15?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_15","name":"Romans2017_15","memoryVerse":"“I consider that our present sufferings are not worth comparing with the glory that will be revealed in us.” – Romans 8:18 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_15_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 8:28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_3","questionText":"3. What is the “good” that God works for His people in all things? (See also Romans 8:29-39.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29-39"}]},{"id":"2017_15_4a","questionText":"4. a. Put Romans 8:28 in your own words. What assurances does this verse offer the believer in every situation?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28"}]},{"id":"2017_15_4b","questionText":"4. b. How might you pray when struggling with things that you wonder how God will use for good?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_5","questionText":"5. What do you learn about God’s attributes and character from Romans 8:28, and how does this challenge or comfort you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 8:29-30.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_6","questionText":"6.  a.  Briefly explain the following concepts. (For help, see John 6:37, 44; Romans 1:6-7; 3:22-26; 8:17-21;  Ephesians 1:4-5, 11 or other Bible passages.)  Foreknew","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"6:37"},{"book":"John","verse":"6:44"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:6-7"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:22-26"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:17-21"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:4-5"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:11"}]},{"id":"2017_15_6b","questionText":"6.  a.  Predestined","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6c","questionText":"6.  a.  Called","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6d","questionText":"6.  a.   Justified","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6e","questionText":"6.  a.   Glorified","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6f","questionText":"6. b. What does Romans 8:29-30 reveal about God, and why is it good news?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29-30"}]},{"id":"2017_15_7","questionText":"7.  What are some ways God works to conform believers to the image of His Son? What are some reasons many professing believers do not act like Jesus? (See also Romans 5:3-5; 2 Timothy 3:12, 15-16; Hebrews 5:7-8 or other Bible passages.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:3-5"},{"book":"2 Timothy","verse":"3:12"},{"book":"2 Timothy","verse":"3:15-16"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"5:7-8"}]},{"id":"2017_15_8","questionText":"  8. How do you see God at work in your life to make you more Christlike?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 8:31-35.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:31-35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_9","questionText":"  9. List the questions and answers in verses 31-35. What conclusions can you draw based on these questions and answers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_10","questionText":"10. With which of the previous questions are you struggling, and how do the answers encourage you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 8:35-39.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:35-39"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_11","questionText":"11.  Why does Paul quote Psalm 44:22 to answer the questions verse 35 asks? (See also John 16:33.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"44:22"},{"book":"John","verse":"16:33"}]},{"id":"2017_15_12","questionText":"12.  a.  How do “all these things” in verses 35-37 relate to “all things” in verses 28 and 32?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_12b","questionText":"12. b.  How has a deeper understanding of Christ’s love helped you in a specific difficulty this year?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_13","questionText":"13. List things in your life or world events that tempt you to worry or prompt anger and impatience. Use your list to rewrite verses 38-39 as your own statement of confidence in God’s love for you.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 8:28-39.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28-39"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 8:28-39","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28-39"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_16?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_16","name":"Romans2017_16","memoryVerse":"“He who did not spare his own Son, but gave him up for us all — how will he not also, along with him, graciously give us all things?” – Romans 8:32","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_16_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 9:1-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_3","questionText":"3.  What truth does Paul affirm? Why is Paul grieving for the people of Israel and how is he like Moses and Jesus? (For additional help see Exodus 32:30-32; Luke 19:41-44; John 10:11; Romans 9:1-29.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"32:30-32"},{"book":"Luke","verse":"19:41-44"},{"book":"John","verse":"10:11"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-29"}]},{"id":"2017_16_4a","questionText":"4. a. Explain what “cursed” means in Romans 9:3 and whether any believer might ever be “cut off” from Christ. What do you think is Paul’s point? (See also Romans 8:1, 35, 38-39.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:3"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:35"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:38-39"}]},{"id":"2017_16_4b","questionText":"4. b. How does Paul’s love for the unbelieving people of Israel model the way believers should respond to unbelievers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_5","questionText":"5. Consider the spiritual advantages God has given you. What are their benefits? How are they sometimes squandered? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 9:6-13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:6-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_6a","questionText":"6. a. How is God true to His Word despite the unbelief of the majority of the Israelite people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_6b","questionText":"6. b. What examples does Paul give to prove that physical birth never automatically makes anyone God’s child? (See also Romans 2:28-29.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:28-29"}]},{"id":"2017_16_7","questionText":"7. How do these verses show salvation is by grace and not human effort? What hope does this give you for your unbelieving family members, friends or co-workers?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 9:14-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:14-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_8","questionText":"8. What does Paul’s use of Bible history reveal about God and how He elects to work out His righteous and holy will? How does this compare with your understanding?  (See also Exodus 7:3, 13; 8:32; 14:4.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"7:3"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"7:13"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"8:32"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"14:4"}]},{"id":"2017_16_9a","questionText":"9. a. From verses 20-21, explain in your own words the problem with people accusing God of injustice. (See also Isaiah 29:16; 64:8; Jeremiah 18:6; 2 Timothy 2:20.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"29:16"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"64:8"},{"book":"Jeremiah","verse":"18:6"},{"book":"2 Timothy","verse":"2:20"}]},{"id":"2017_16_9b","questionText":"9. b. Give examples of how people today (perhaps even you) use similar reasons to excuse sin or accuse God of injustice.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_10","questionText":"10. How has God shown you mercy when your heart was hard, and how have you responded to Him? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 9:22-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:22-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_11","questionText":"11. In verses 22-24, how and why does God demonstrate His power and mercy?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_12","questionText":"12.  What about the riches of God’s glory move you to prayer, praise or practical actions? (See also Ephesians 1:7-8, 18-23; 2:1-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:7-8"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:18-23"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-10"}]},{"id":"2017_16_13","questionText":"13. What do you learn about God’s mercy and grace to Jews and Gentiles from the Hosea and Isaiah quotations?  (See also Romans 11:3-6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:3-6"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 9:1-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 9:1-29","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-29"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_17?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_17","name":"Romans2017_17","memoryVerse":"“What if he did this to make the riches of his glory known to the objects of his mercy, whom he prepared in advance for glory – even us, whom he also called, not only from the Jews but also from the Gentiles?” – Romans 9:23-24 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes with references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_17_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 9:30-33.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:30-33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_3","questionText":"3. What was the difference in the way the Gentiles and Israel approached righteousness? What were the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_4","questionText":"4. How is daily pursuing righteous behavior different from striving for righteous standing? What role does faith play?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_5","questionText":"5. Who is “the stumbling stone”? What about “the stumbling stone” causes people to stumble or fall?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 10:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_6","questionText":"6. Why would Paul so strongly desire the Israelites be saved? How has God called you to pray for and minister tothose you desire to be saved?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_7","questionText":"7. What knowledge did the Israelites lack that caused their zeal to be misdirected? What does zealous behaviorwithout true knowledge of Jesus look like in today’s world? (Focus on behaviors without naming groups.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_8","questionText":"8. Explain Romans 10:4 in your own words. (You may want to read additional Bible translations to help you.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:4"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 10:5-9.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:5-9"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_9","questionText":"9. What conclusions does Paul make in light of these verses? (Note: Romans 10:5-7 can be interpreted in  various ways.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:5-7"}]},{"id":"2017_17_10","questionText":"10. What must a person do to be saved? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_11","questionText":"11. How would you take each phrase of verse 9 and explain its meaning and importance to an unbeliever?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 10:10-13","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:10-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_12","questionText":"12. Share different aspects of the word “heart” from the following references: Matthew 6:21; 12:34; Romans 1:21-22; Galatians 4:6. As you meditate on these verses, what is God showing you about your heart? ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"6:21"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"12:34"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:21-22"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"4:6"}]},{"id":"2017_17_13","questionText":"13. How does verse 13 relate to and clarify verse 11? According to these verses, to whom is salvation available?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_14","questionText":"14. When did you (or will you) call on the name of the Lord for salvation?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 9:30-10:13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:30-10:13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_15","questionText":"15. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 9:30-10:13","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:30-10:13"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_18?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_18","name":"Romans Lesson 182017_18","memoryVerse":"“If you declare with your mouth, ‘Jesus is Lord,’ and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved.” – Romans 10:9","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_18_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 10:14-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:14-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_18_3","questionText":"3. How does Paul describe the steps to believing in Jesus Christ in verses 14-15?  Share your personal progression through the steps to believing in Jesus.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_4","questionText":"4. Summarize the “good news” from your study of Romans.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_5","questionText":"5. What is your role in sharing the good news with family, friends and the world?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 10:14-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:14-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_18_6","questionText":"6. Give at least one point about the proclamation of the gospel from each reference.   Matthew 28:18-20","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"28:18-20"}]},{"id":"2017_18_6b","questionText":"6.   Acts 1:8","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"1:8"}]},{"id":"2017_18_6c","questionText":"6.   Acts 13:46-47","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"13:46-47"}]},{"id":"2017_18_6d","questionText":"6.   Romans 15:20","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:20"}]},{"id":"2017_18_6e","questionText":"6.   2 Corinthians 2:12-14","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"2:12-14"}]},{"id":"2017_18_6f","questionText":"6.   2 Corinthians 10:15-16","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"10:15-16"}]},{"id":"2017_18_7","questionText":"7. To whom does Paul’s quotation from Isaiah 52:7 refer? Why were their feet beautiful?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"52:7"}]},{"id":"2017_18_8","questionText":"  8. How is God calling you to take His message of grace into places filled with despair?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 10:16-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:16-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_18_9","questionText":"  9. From a human perspective, why do people not respond positively to the good news when they hear it?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_10","questionText":"10. According to verse 17, from where does faith come? What does this teach about the importance of studying the Bible?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_11","questionText":"11. Share a time the Bible brought forth or strengthened your faith?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 10:18-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:18-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_18_12","questionText":"12. Try to describe Paul’s logic in verses 18-21. How would you explain the differences in hearing, understanding and believing?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_13","questionText":"13. To whom were Moses and Isaiah referring in verses 19-20? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_14","questionText":"14. Where has God strategically placed you to share the Bible’s truths? How might you encourage someone today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Romans 10:14-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:14-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_18_15","questionText":"15. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_18_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 10:14–21","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:14"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_19?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_19","name":"Romans Lesson 192017_19","memoryVerse":"“Consequently, faith comes from hearing the message, and the message is heard through the word about Christ.” – Romans 10:17","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_19_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 11:1-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:1-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_19_3","questionText":"3. Explain Paul’s reasoning as to why God has not rejected the Jewish people. How do Paul’s testimony and Elijah’s experience strengthen his explanation?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_4","questionText":"4. What is a remnant? How is the remnant chosen?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_5","questionText":"5. What is the connection between grace and the elect?  How does that impact your understanding of election?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 11:1-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:1-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_19_6","questionText":"6. From verse 7, what did Israel seek? Why did they not obtain it? (See Romans 9:31-33)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:31-33"}]},{"id":"2017_19_7","questionText":"7. How do the following passages help you understand verses 7-10?  Isaiah 29:10-14","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"29:10-14"}]},{"id":"2017_19_7b","questionText":"7.  Psalm 69:22-26","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"69:22-26"}]},{"id":"2017_19_7c","questionText":"7.  Matthew 13:12-15","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"13:12-15"}]},{"id":"2017_19_7d","questionText":"7.  John 12:37-43","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"12:37-43"}]},{"id":"2017_19_7e","questionText":"7.  Acts 28:24-28","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"28:24-28"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 11:11-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:11-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_19_8","questionText":"  8. Explain Paul’s reasoning in verses 11-16. What good has come from Israel’s rejection?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_9","questionText":"  9. Without pressing the illustration too far, give in a few words about the point Paul made in verses 17-24. How does this passage address the boasting believer?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_10","questionText":"10. How has God demonstrated both kindness and sternness in your life? What have been the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 11:25-32.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:25-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_19_11","questionText":"11. What could “all Israel” mean? Which interpretation seems most likely based on what you know about God and His Word? (There are several interpretations.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_12","questionText":"12. What will happen to Israel?  How can we be sure?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_13","questionText":"13. What do these verses reveal about God’s work and character? How do these truths comfort or challenge you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_14","questionText":"14. How did God show mercy to both Jews and Gentiles? Explain in your own words why all people need the mercy of God.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 11:1-32.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:1-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_19_15","questionText":"15. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_19_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 11:1-32.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:1-32"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_20?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_20","name":"Romans Lesson 202017_20","memoryVerse":"“I do not want you to be ignorant of this mystery, brothers and sisters, so that you may not be conceited: Israel has experienced a hardening in part until the full number of the Gentiles has come in.” – Romans 11:25 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_20_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 11:33-36.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:33-36"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_20_3","questionText":"3. Paul breaks into praise to God in verses 33-36. What reasons expressed in verses 25-32 would cause him to do this?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:25-32"}]},{"id":"2017_20_4","questionText":"4. In chapter 11, how did Paul describe God’s plan for saving the Gentiles?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:1-36"}]},{"id":"2017_20_5","questionText":"5. What has God done recently that would cause you to break into praise of Him?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 11:33-34.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:33-34"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_20_6","questionText":"6. For which attributes does Paul praise God in verse 33?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_7","questionText":"7. Share aspects of these attributes from the following verses.  How do these verses relate to your present circumstances?  1 Kings 8:39","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_7b","questionText":"7.  Job 9:4","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Job","verse":"9:4"}]},{"id":"2017_20_7c","questionText":"7.  Job 28:12-28","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Job","verse":"28:12-28"}]},{"id":"2017_20_7d","questionText":"7.  Psalm 147:4","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"147:4"}]},{"id":"2017_20_7e","questionText":"7.  Proverbs 3:19","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"3:19"}]},{"id":"2017_20_8","questionText":"8. Try to trace God’s wise ways in one area of your life. (Examples include your education, employment, family or other.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 11:33-34.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:33-34"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_20_9","questionText":"  9. What is Paul asking in verse 34? What is the answer?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_10","questionText":"10. How do people’s perceptions of themselves differ from the biblical perspective given in these verses? (See Job 38:1-7; Job 42:1-6; Psalm 8:1-9; Isaiah 40:13-28.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Job","verse":"38:1-7"},{"book":"Job","verse":"42:1-6"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"8:1-9"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"40:13-28"}]},{"id":"2017_20_11","questionText":"11. How do these attributes of God comfort or challenge you? In what area of your life are you clinging to or forgetting these attributes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 11:35-36.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:35-36"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_20_12","questionText":"12.  What has God given to people in general and to you specifically?  How will you respond to all God has given you? (See Genesis 1:27-30; John 3:16; Acts 17:24-28 or any other Scripture.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"1:27-30"},{"book":"John","verse":"3:16"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"17:24-28"}]},{"id":"2017_20_13","questionText":"13. What can people give to God? (See Job 35:7-8, 41:11 or any other Scripture.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Job","verse":"35:7-8"},{"book":"Job","verse":"41:11"}]},{"id":"2017_20_14","questionText":"14. How might people place God under obligation to repay them today (knowingly or unknowingly)?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_15","questionText":"15. How are all things from God, through God and to God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_16","questionText":"16. For what reason did God create the universe? (See Isaiah 43:7; Ephesians 1:5-10; Revelation 4:11.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"43:7"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:5-10"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"4:11"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Romans 11:33-36.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:33-36"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_20_17","questionText":"17. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_20_18","questionText":"18. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 11:33-36","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:33-36"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_21?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_21","name":"Romans Lesson 212017_21","memoryVerse":"“For from him and through him and for him are all things. To him be the glory forever! Amen.” – Romans 11:36","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_21_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 12:1-2.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:1-2"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_21_3","questionText":"3.  What specific points from Romans was Paul thinking about as he started this section with the word “therefore”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_4","questionText":"4. What are Christians to do as a result of the truths learned through the Romans study?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_5","questionText":"5.  What qualities or behaviors should make Christians different from the world around them? Tell about a Christian who has had a profound influence in your life.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 12:1.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:1"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_21_6","questionText":"6.  What do you learn about God and His mercy from the following verses? Romans 9:15","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:15"}]},{"id":"2017_21_6b","questionText":"6. Romans 9:23","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:23"}]},{"id":"2017_21_6c","questionText":"6. Ephesians 2:4-5","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:4-5"}]},{"id":"2017_21_6d","questionText":"6. 1 Peter 1:3","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"1:3"}]},{"id":"2017_21_6e","questionText":"7  How has God shown His mercy to your country, to your family and to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_8f","questionText":"8.  Define “sacrifice.” Compare and contrast the Old Testament sacrifices of animals with the kind of sacrifice Paul is urging Christians to be. (See Leviticus 16; Hebrews 10:1-10; and Romans 6:3-4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"10:1-10"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:3-4"}]},{"id":"2017_21_9g","questionText":"  9.  Share both ordinary and extraordinary examples in which people today offer their bodies as living sacrifices.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 12:2; Galatians 1:3-5; and Ephesians 2:1-2.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:2"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"1:3-5"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-2"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_21_10h","questionText":"10.  How is the word “world” used in this context?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_11i","questionText":"11.  How is the pattern of this world described in 1 John 2:15-17? How would you describe the pattern of this world in your own words?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 John","verse":"2:15-17"}]},{"id":"2017_21_12j","questionText":"12.  In what ways has the pattern of the world crept into your thinking, choices, habits, outlook, relationships or priorities?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 12:1-2.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:1-2"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_21_13k","questionText":"13.  According to Romans 12:2; 2 Corinthians 3:18 and Philippians 2:13, how is a person transformed?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:2"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"3:18"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"2:13"}]},{"id":"2017_21_14l","questionText":"14.  How does a person renew their mind? How are you helping to renew the minds of others including the next generation?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_15m","questionText":"15.  How does Paul describe God’s will? How does this differ from the world’s (and some Christians’) ideas of God’s will?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_21_16n","questionText":"16.  What do these verses teach about God’s good, pleasing and perfect will? John 14:15","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"14:15"}]},{"id":"2017_21_NaN","questionText":"16. 2 Corinthians 10:5","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"10:5"}]},{"id":"2017_21_16c","questionText":"16. 1 Thessalonians 4:3-7","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Thessalonians","verse":"4:3-7"}]},{"id":"2017_21_16d","questionText":"16. James 5:13-16","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"James","verse":"5:13-16"}]},{"id":"2017_21_16e","questionText":"16. 1 Peter 2:15","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"2:15"}]},{"id":"2017_21_16f","questionText":"16. 1 Peter 3:17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"3:17"}]},{"id":"2017_21_16g","questionText":"16. 1 Peter 4:1-11","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"4:1-11"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 12:1-2.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:1-2"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_21_17","questionText":"17. How has your understanding of God’s will changed or developed through this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life? No homiletics for administrative and discussion leaders","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_22?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_22","name":"Romans Lesson 222017_22","memoryVerse":"“Therefore, I urge you, brothers and sisters, in view of God’s mercy, to offer your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and pleasing to God – this is your true and proper worship. Do not conform to the pattern of this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind. Then you will be able to test and approve what God’s will is – his good, pleasing and perfect will.” – Romans 12:1-2","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_22_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 12:3.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:3"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_22_3","questionText":"3. On what basis does Paul give his instructions? Why is that important?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_4","questionText":"4. What warning does he give? What possible errors can occur as we evaluate ourselves?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_5","questionText":"5. How does the phrase “measure of faith” guide a believer’s self-evaluation and evaluation of others?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_6","questionText":"6. Why is it important to have a proper evaluation of yourself before relating to others in the church?  What is God revealing to you about the way you relate to others?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 12:4-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:4-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_22_7","questionText":"7. To what does Paul compare Christians? How does this illustration help you understand the way Christians are to relate to one another?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_8","questionText":"  8. List some ways each member of the body belongs to all the other members. List some ways each member of the body has individual responsibilities.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 12:4-5 and Ephesians 4:1-6","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:4-5"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:1-6"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_22_9","questionText":"  9. According to Scripture, who comprises the body of Christ? What unites the body of Christ?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_10","questionText":"10. What instructions does Paul give to maintain unity within local congregations and in the universal Church?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_11","questionText":"11. How are you contributing to, or eroding, unity within the body of Christ in your local congregation or in the universal Church?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 12:6-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:6-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_22_12","questionText":"12. Share truths concerning God’s gifts to Christians from the following verses: 1 Corinthians 7:7b","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"7:7"}]},{"id":"2017_22_12b","questionText":"12. 1 Corinthians 12:4-6","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"12:4-6"}]},{"id":"2017_22_12c","questionText":"12. Ephesians 4:11-13","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:11-13"}]},{"id":"2017_22_12d","questionText":"12. 1 Peter 4:10-11","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"4:10-11"}]},{"id":"2017_22_13","questionText":"13.  List the seven gifts in these verses. Write how each should be exercised along with specific ways this can be done in a local church.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_14","questionText":"14. Which of the gifts has God given you, and what opportunities has He given you to use His gifts?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Romans 12:3-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:3-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_22_15","questionText":"15. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_22_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 12:3-8","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:3-8"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_23?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_23","name":"Romans Lesson 232017_23","memoryVerse":"“So in Christ we, though many, form one body, and each member belongs to all the others.” – Romans 12:5","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_23_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 12:9-13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_23_3","questionText":"3. What does Paul want you to keep in mind as you read these verses? How might remembering help you obey these commands? (See Romans 12:1-2.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:1-2"}]},{"id":"2017_23_4","questionText":"4. Compare Paul’s description of love with the popular view of love in your culture. How does hating what is evil relate to sincere love?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_5","questionText":"5. Compare the Bible’s description of evil with the popular view of evil in your culture.  Proverbs 8:13","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"8:13"}]},{"id":"2017_23_5b","questionText":"5.  Proverbs 13:5","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Proverbs","verse":"13:5"}]},{"id":"2017_23_5c","questionText":"5.  Ecclesiastes 3:8","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ecclesiastes","verse":"3:8"}]},{"id":"2017_23_5d","questionText":"5.  Isaiah 61:8","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"61:8"}]},{"id":"2017_23_5e","questionText":"5.  Amos 5:15","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Amos","verse":"5:15"}]},{"id":"2017_23_5f","questionText":"5.  Luke 14:26","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Luke","verse":"14:26"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 12:9-13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_23_6","questionText":"6. Which individuals or groups is it hard for you to honor above yourself? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_7","questionText":"7. Put verse 11 in your own words. How is it relevant to your current circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_8","questionText":"8. Which of Paul’s commands in Romans 12:9-13 is hardest for you to obey? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-13"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 12:14-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:14-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_23_9","questionText":"  9. How does a person bless persecutors? Whom might you come alongside and bless? (See Matthew 5:44; Luke 6:27-28 or any other Scriptures.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"5:44"},{"book":"Luke","verse":"6:27-28"}]},{"id":"2017_23_10","questionText":"10. What strategies for healthy relationships are found in these verses? What opportunities is God giving you to practice these commands?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_11","questionText":"11. How does pride destroy relationships? Share an example of how humility has mended or restored relationships.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_12","questionText":"12. How have you been helped by someone who has come alongside you to weep, grieve or mourn with you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 12:17-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:17-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_23_13","questionText":"13. Share ways people repay evil for evil today. Which ones are tempting to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_14","questionText":"14. Give examples from Scripture of those who did not repay evil for evil. What were the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_15","questionText":"15. What is the believer’s responsibility to their enemies? What does Scripture promise God will do?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_16","questionText":"16. How can a person live the kind of life Paul is commanding in Romans 12:9-21?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-21"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 12:9-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_23_17","questionText":"17. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_23_18","questionText":"18. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 12:9-21","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-21"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_24?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_24","name":"Romans Lesson 242017_24","memoryVerse":"“Love must be sincere. Hate what is evil; cling to what is good.” – Romans 12:9","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_24_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 13:1-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:1-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_24_3","questionText":"3.  Define “be subject to” or “submit.” Who is to submit to governing authorities, and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_4","questionText":"4.  Give reasons people struggle with submitting to authority? Which is your greatest struggle?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_5","questionText":"5.  Give examples of when refusing to submit to governing authority is acceptable in God’s eyes? (See Daniel 3 and 6; Acts 5:29)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Daniel","verse":"3:1-30"},{"book":"Daniel","verse":"6:1-28"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"5:29"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 13:1-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:1-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_24_6","questionText":"6.  When you refuse to submit to moral and legal authority, against whom are you ultimately rebelling?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_7","questionText":"7. How does respect for authority glorify God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_8","questionText":"8. How is God convicting you regarding these verses?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 13:3-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:3-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_24_9","questionText":"  9.  How are rulers God’s servants for good, even if they are evil? What comfort and confidence can you have when you receive evil instead of good from a leader?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_10","questionText":"10.  What reasons does Paul give for submitting to authorities? Can you think of other reasons?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_11","questionText":"11.  What kind of example do you set for your children and others who watch your response to governing authorities?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 13:6-7.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:6-7"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_24_12","questionText":"12.  What did Jesus say about paying taxes? (See Luke 20:22-25.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Luke","verse":"20:22-25"}]},{"id":"2017_24_13","questionText":"13.  What are the purposes of taxes? What should be your attitude toward paying them?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_14","questionText":"14.   From the following verses, list those to whom we are to show respect and honor.  What are some specific ways you can show respect or honor to these people?  Exodus 20:12","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"20:12"}]},{"id":"2017_24_14b","questionText":"14.   Leviticus 19:32","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Leviticus","verse":"19:32"}]},{"id":"2017_24_14c","questionText":"14.  1 Timothy 5:17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Timothy","verse":"5:17"}]},{"id":"2017_24_14d","questionText":"14.   1 Timothy 6:15b-16","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Timothy","verse":"6:15-16"}]},{"id":"2017_24_14e","questionText":"14.   1 Peter 2:13-17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"2:13-17"}]},{"id":"2017_24_15","questionText":"15. How can you show honor and respect to someone whose decisions and character differ from yours?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Romans 13:1-7.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:1-7"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_24_16","questionText":"16.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_24_17","questionText":"17. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders:  Romans 13:1-7","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:1-7"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_25?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_25","name":"Romans Lesson 252017_25","memoryVerse":"“Let everyone be subject to the governing authorities, for there is no authority except that which God has established. The authorities that exist have been established by God.” – Romans 13:1","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_25_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 13:8-10 with Romans 12:9-21; 1 Corinthians 13:1-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:8-10"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:9-21"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"13:1-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_25_3","questionText":"3. Why can Christians never fully satisfy the continuing debt to love one another?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_4","questionText":"4. Compare and contrast legalistic versus loving obedience to the commands in verse 9. Which one do you lean toward?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_5","questionText":"5. Whom is it that you struggle to love? What does that reveal about them and you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_6","questionText":"6.  How would you explain “love is the fulfillment of the law”?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 13:11-12.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:11-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_25_7","questionText":"7.  What does Paul mean by “salvation” and “the day is almost here”? What is Paul’s motive in reminding believers our salvation is nearer now?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_8","questionText":"8.  How does the Bible describe this “present time” as the Lord’s return draws nearer? (Use any Bible verses, such as Galatians 1:4; Luke 19:44.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Galatians","verse":"1:4"},{"book":"Luke","verse":"19:44"}]},{"id":"2017_25_9","questionText":"  9.  List ways you see Christians slumbering presently. In what ways might you be slumbering?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 13:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_25_10","questionText":"10. How has your culture normalized behaviors the Bible calls indecent?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_11","questionText":"11.  Using verse 13 as help, what does behaving decently look like?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_12","questionText":"12. How is God convicting you regarding these verses?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 13:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_25_13","questionText":"13.  What is the “armor of light”? (Use Ephesians 6:10-18 and Galatians 5:22-23 to help you.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"6:10-18"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:22-23"}]},{"id":"2017_25_14","questionText":"14.  How does knowing Jesus is Light help you understand His character and works? (See John 8:12; 1 John 1:5-7 or any other Scriptures you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"8:12"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"1:5-7"}]},{"id":"2017_25_15","questionText":"15.  How will you clothe yourself with the Lord Jesus Christ instead of gratifying the desires of the sinful nature?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 13:8-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:8-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_25_16","questionText":"16.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_25_17","questionText":"17. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 13:8-14","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:8-14"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_26?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_26","name":"Romans Lesson 262017_26","memoryVerse":"“Rather, clothe yourselves with the Lord Jesus Christ, and do not think about how to gratify the desires of the flesh.”  – Romans 13:14 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_26_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 14:1-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"14:1-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_26_3","questionText":"3. How does Paul encourage weaker and stronger believers to respond to one another?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_4","questionText":"4.  What types of disputable practices are mentioned in the passage? What distinguishes a disputable practice from a forbidden practice?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_5","questionText":"5. What similar standard and conviction do both the weaker and stronger believers share?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 14:9-12.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"14:9-12"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_26_6","questionText":"6. Which practices are you willing to forego for the sake of a brother or sister in Christ?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_7","questionText":"7. What is the reason we should not judge or look down on our fellow believers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_8","questionText":"8. What will happen at God’s judgment seat? Why is that a reason not to judge others now?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 14:13-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"14:13-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_26_9","questionText":"9. From these verses, share several responsibilities Christians have toward fellow believers.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_10","questionText":"10. Why was Paul able to say in verse 14 that no food is unclean in itself? What makes food unclean for a particular person?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_11","questionText":"11. How does a believer cause another believer to stumble today?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_12","questionText":"12. How does Paul describe the kingdom of God? Why does Paul make this distinction?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 14:19-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"14:19-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_26_13","questionText":"13. How might too much concern over disputable matters destroy the work of God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_14","questionText":"14. What are the best practices when dealing with other believers and disputable matters?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_15","questionText":"15. What conclusion does Paul draw for stronger and weaker believers in disputable matters?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_16","questionText":"16. What behavior will you seek to change in yourself with God’s help because of studying this lesson?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"14:1-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_26_17","questionText":"17. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_26_18","questionText":"18. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 14","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_27?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_27","name":"Romans Lesson 272017_27","memoryVerse":"“For the kingdom of God is not a matter of eating and drinking, but of righteousness, peace and joy in the Holy Spirit.” – Romans 14:17","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_27_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 15:1-6.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:1-6"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_27_3","questionText":"3. Share some of the privileges and some of the responsibilities of Christians.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_4","questionText":"4. How does pleasing our neighbors to build them up differ from “people-pleasing”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_5","questionText":"5. Share an example from Scripture of Jesus Christ not living to please Himself. How is that relevant to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_6","questionText":"6. How would you describe people who live to please themselves? What similarities and differences do you share with that description?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 15:4-6.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:4-6"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_27_7","questionText":"7.  What are several benefits that come from studying Scripture? How have you realized these benefits through your study of Romans?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_8","questionText":"8. How does a “spirit of unity” differ from uniformity or agreement on all matters? With what groups or individual believers do you struggle to uphold unity?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_9","questionText":"  9. How does Christian unity glorify God? (See 1 Corinthians 12:12-27; Ephesians 4:1-16; Colossians 1:15-20.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"12:12-27"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:1-16"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"1:15-20"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 15:7-13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:7-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_27_10","questionText":"10. Why is it important for believers to accept other believers? How does Christ’s acceptance of you help you in accepting others?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_11","questionText":"11. Which Old Testament verses are quoted in Romans 15:9-12? What is the subject of these quotations?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:9-12"}]},{"id":"2017_27_12","questionText":"12.  a.  What is the significance of Paul using Old Testament references to illustrate unity between the Jews and  Gentiles in Christ?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_12b","questionText":"12. b.  How does this understanding help you re-evaluate fellow believers with whom you struggle to be unified?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 15:13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_27_13","questionText":"13. What is the relationship between trust and hope? (See also 1 Timothy 1:1; Hebrews 6:18-19; Hebrews 11:1 or any other verses for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Timothy","verse":"1:1"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"6:18-19"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"11:1"}]},{"id":"2017_27_14","questionText":"14. What does the relationship between trust and hope teach you about God? How does this comfort or challenge you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_15","questionText":"15. For whom will you pray the blessings of Romans 15:13?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:13"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Romans 15:1-13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:1-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_27_16","questionText":"16. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_27_17","questionText":"17. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 15:1-13","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:1-13"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_28?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_28","name":"Romans Lesson 282017_28","memoryVerse":"“May the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace as you trust in him, so that you may overflow with hope by the power of the Holy Spirit.” – Romans 15:13","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_28_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 15:14-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:14-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_28_3","questionText":"3. For what three things does Paul commend his readers? How will you encourage fellow believers this week?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_4","questionText":"4. How do you reconcile Paul’s commendations with his prior warnings and instructions? (See Romans 12:1-15:13.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"12:1-15:13"}]},{"id":"2017_28_5","questionText":"5. Describe the role of a priest in the Bible. (Use Scripture or a Bible dictionary.) In verse 16, how does Paul describe his “priestly duty” and the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 15:17-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:17-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_28_6","questionText":"6. How does what Paul glories in compare with the things in which your culture rejoices or boasts?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_7","questionText":"7.  Whom did Paul credit for his success with the Gentiles? In what area of your life are you claiming success when it rightfully belongs to God? (See Deuteronomy 8:17.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"8:17"}]},{"id":"2017_28_8","questionText":"8. How do Paul’s aim and ambition in sharing the gospel compare with yours?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_9","questionText":"  9. What opportunities is God giving you to share the gospel?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 15:22-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:22-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_28_10","questionText":"10.  In verses 22-24, what did Paul long to do, and why did his longing go unfulfilled?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_11","questionText":"11.  What does this reveal about both Paul’s and your understandings of pursuing personal fulfillment?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_12","questionText":"12.  What two points does Paul make about the financial gift he was taking to Jerusalem? What principles about giving can you draw from these two points?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 15:30-33 with Acts 20:22-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:30-33"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"20:22-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_28_13","questionText":"13.  What dangers was Paul facing as he went to Jerusalem?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_14","questionText":"14. What did Paul ask for in his struggle? What does this communicate about Paul’s view of prayer?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_15","questionText":"15.  What specific prayer requests did Paul ask for himself and with what goal?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_16","questionText":"16. Paul could have chosen any attribute of God for verse 33. What might have been his reason to choose “God of peace”? In what area of your life will you ask the God of peace to minister to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 15:14-33.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:14-33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_28_17","questionText":"17. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_28_18","questionText":"18. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 15:14-33","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"15:14-33"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_29?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_29","name":"Romans Lesson 292017_29","memoryVerse":"“Therefore I glory in Christ Jesus in my service to God.” – Romans 15:17","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_29_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 16:1-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"16:1-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_29_3","questionText":"3. Why would Paul include this list of people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_4","questionText":"4. What does this list reveal about Paul’s ministry? What principles for Christian ministry are revealed through this list?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_5","questionText":"5. According to these verses, what are some of the ways people loved and supported Paul? What are some of the ways God has provided for you through others?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_6","questionText":"6. Which of all these people interests you the most? Why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 16:17-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"16:17-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_29_7","questionText":"7. What does Paul’s warning reveal about Christian ministry?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_8","questionText":"8. According to these verses, how are divisive and deceptive people recognizable? What should Christians do about them?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_9","questionText":"  9. Give practical examples of what it looks like to be “wise about what is good and innocent about what is evil.”","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_10","questionText":"10. What assurances does Paul offer in verse 20? How does this give you hope in your present circumstances?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 16:20-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"16:20-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_29_11","questionText":"11. What do you learn about the people who are with Paul?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_12","questionText":"12. Who is on your list of people who have supported and encouraged you in life or your Christian service? How will you encourage them this week? 13 What does this teach you about the value of relationships in life or Christian ministry?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 16:25-27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"16:25-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_29_14","questionText":"14. Put verses 25-27 in your own words.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_15","questionText":"15. From your study of Romans, what is the message Paul proclaimed about Jesus Christ?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_16","questionText":"16. What was the mystery to which Paul referred in verse 25? (See Ephesians 3:2-6 and Colossians 1:27.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"3:2-6"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"1:27"}]},{"id":"2017_29_17","questionText":"17. How will you give glory to God for all He has done in history and in your own personal life this year?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Read Romans 16:1-27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"16:1-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_29_18","questionText":"18. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_29_19","questionText":"19. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 16.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_30?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_30","name":"Romans2017_30","memoryVerse":"“To the only wise God be glory forever through Jesus Christ! Amen.” – Romans 16:27","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2017_30_1","questionText":"1. What did you learn about God through the study of Romans, and what difference has that made in your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2017_30_2","questionText":"2. What did you learn about yourself during the study, and how did God use that to draw you closer to Him? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2017_30_3","questionText":"3. In what ways did you experience God changing your thoughts, attitudes, desires and actions this year? How did you see Him work in the lives of the children you bring to BSF?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2017_30_4","questionText":"4. How has your relationship with Jesus Christ changed this year, and what impact has that had on your relationships with others?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2017_30_5","questionText":"5. Now that you have completed the study of Romans, what do you think God’s plan for you includes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY:","questions":[{"id":"2017_30_6","questionText":"6. What do you want to tell others about God’s work in your life during the study of Romans? Who might need that encouragement to trust Jesus at this time?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}}}